<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sacred ordinance of ordination, by imposition of the hands of the presbytery. As it was lately held forth in a sermon preached at the solemn ordination of ministers in the city of Norwich June 11. 1656. / By John Brinsley minister of the Gospel at Great Yarmouth. VVhereunto is also affixed the word of exhortation given to the persons then and there ordained, being usefull to all others of the same tribe. By Nic. Ganning, B.D. minister of the Gospel at Barnham-Broom.</title>
            <author>Brinsley, John, 1660-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1601_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208903</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 202:E1601[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sacred ordinance of ordination, by imposition of the hands of the presbytery. As it was lately held forth in a sermon preached at the solemn ordination of ministers in the city of Norwich June 11. 1656. / By John Brinsley minister of the Gospel at Great Yarmouth. VVhereunto is also affixed the word of exhortation given to the persons then and there ordained, being usefull to all others of the same tribe. By Nic. Ganning, B.D. minister of the Gospel at Barnham-Broom.</title>
                  <author>Brinsley, John, 1660-1665.</author>
                  <author>Ganning, Nicholas, d. 1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Rob. Ibbitson, for Tho. Newberry, at the sign of the three Lyons in Corn-hill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An exhortation given to the late ordained ministers after the ordination, in the close of the day thereof, Norwich June 11. 1656" has caption title; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 2".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st IV, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Ordination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Sacred Ordinance OF ORDINATION, By Impoſition of the Hands of the PRESBYTERY.</p>
            <p>As it was lately held forth in a Sermon Preached at the ſolemn Ordination of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the City of <hi>Norwich June</hi> 11. 1656.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Brinſley</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at Great <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhereunto is alſo affixed the <hi>Word of Exhortation</hi> given to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then and there Ordained, being uſefull to all others of the ſame Tribe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nic. Ganning,</hi> B. D. Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Barnham-Broom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Rob. Ibbitſon,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Newberry,</hi> at the Sign of the three Lyons in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:2"/>
            <head>To the deſervedly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the faithful Diſpenſers of the Myſteries of Chriſt in the County of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Eſpecially ſuch as were Aſſiſtant or preſent at the late ſolemn Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Miniſters in the City of <hi>Norwich. June</hi> 11. 1656.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Much eſteemed in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat was lately at the <hi>requeſt</hi> of ſome of you Preached, is now (with ſome ſmall <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments</hi>) upon the like ſcore Publiſhed. Wherein you have a breif account of a <hi>Goſpel-Ordinance,</hi> a leading, and (take it in a qualified ſenſe) a <hi>Fundamental</hi> Ordinance, upon which all other publick Ordinances (as to the right manner of diſpenſing them) have a dependance, Touching which, we may ſay that it is no ſmall comfort to us, (and wee preſume the like to you) that ſo <hi>many,</hi> ſo <hi>fitted</hi> and <hi>qualified</hi> for the work of the Miniſtery, have in theſe diſſolute and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging
<pb facs="tcp:170143:3"/>times appeared willing to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that in <hi>Gods way.</hi> A <hi>hopeful intimation,</hi> that God hath yet a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſe towards this poor <hi>Church</hi> of his, that hee hath a <hi>Harveſt</hi> yet to bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in this field, whereunto hee is pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſend forth ſuch a ſucceſſion of Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Hereunto you have alſo (at the ſame intreatie) affixed the <hi>latter ſervice</hi> of that day, <hi>the word of Exhortation;</hi> which giveth the like account of what is required at the hands of ſuch <hi>ſervants of the Lord,</hi> as are thus dedicated unto him, and ſo, fitly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as an <hi>Applicatory ſupplement</hi> to the aforeſaid Doctrin. May both theſe conduce to the furthering of that good work, for which they were, and now are intended, wee have what wee aimed at, and ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that God who maketh us in the leaſt degree Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in any ſervice to him and his Church. In the deſires and hopes whereof we ſit down, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your unworthy Brethren and Fellow Labourers in the Lord.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J.B.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N.G.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:3"/>
            <p>THE Sacred Ordinance OF ORDINATION: BY Impoſition of the Hands of the Presbytery.</p>
            <p>As it was lately held forth in a Sermon Preached at the ſolemn Ordination of Miniſters in the City of <hi>Norwich,</hi> June 11. Anno. 1656.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Brinſley</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at Great <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Ibbitſon,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Newberry,</hi> at the Sign of the three Lyons in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> over againſt the Great-Conduit, 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170143:4"/>
            <head>THE SACRED ORDINANCE OF ORDINATION: BY Impoſition of the hands of the PRESBYTERY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 TIM. 4.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Neglect not the Gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Propheſy, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this <hi>Text,</hi> which I have now ſingled forth; as being very ſuitable to the preſent <hi>Occaſion,</hi> wee have an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical charge</hi> directed by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to his Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> therein
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170143:5"/>(to break in upon the words abruptly) we may take notice of two things. The <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> and the <hi>matter.</hi> The <hi>object,</hi> or thing, whereabout this charge is given, which in the general is here ſaid to be a <hi>Gift, [the gift that is in thee]</hi> then more particularly deſcribed and ſet forth by the <hi>manner,</hi> or <hi>means</hi> of collating and conferring it, which is partly <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> partly <hi>Ordinary.</hi> Extraordinary and <hi>occaſional [which was given thee by propheſy]</hi> Ordinary and <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental [with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Matter,</hi> what it is that he here giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him in charge concerning this <hi>gift, viz.</hi> that hee ſhould not <hi>neglect</hi> it <hi>[neglect not the Gift which is in thee, which was given thee by Propheſy, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the particulars, which here offer themſelves to our conſideration; which (through divine aſſiſtance) I ſhall touch upon ſeverally, but very briefly, rather glancing at each of them, than inſiſting upon any of them, I begin with the firſt, the <hi>object</hi> of this Charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Gift which is in thee]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>gift,</hi> or <hi>grace,</hi> or <hi>gift of grace</hi> (for ſo the word properly ſignifieth)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what <hi>gift?</hi> what <hi>grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer, wee may take notice of two ſorts of <hi>gifts</hi> or <hi>graces</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170143:5"/>ſpoken of in Scripture.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> non tantum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam gratis da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ſed etiam gratiam gratum facientem ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat. C. A. Lapide ad Text.</note> In the <hi>Schools</hi> commonly known and differenced by thoſe obvious tearms, of <hi>gratiae gratum facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; gratiae gratis datae</hi> (which tearms though being exactly ſcanned, they are not ſo proper, but liable to juſt exception, yet, in as much as they have been long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and being warily underſtood, they may be ſafely and profitably retained) <hi>graces</hi> rendring <hi>acceptable,</hi> and <hi>graces</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>ſerviceable.</hi> The former, the <hi>graces of ſanctification,</hi> wherewith a man being indued (being firſt <hi>juſtified</hi> by the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi>) commeth to do that which is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, the latter, <hi>graces of edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> wherby a man is inabled to do ſervice unto others. Now of this latter kind is the <hi>gift</hi> or <hi>grace,</hi> which here we meet with, a <hi>gift</hi> given unto <hi>Timothy,</hi> for the benefit of others. That is agreed upon at all hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But yet the queſtion goeth on? <hi>what gift was this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here I finde <hi>Expoſitors</hi> not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Some underſtanding it of an <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gift,</hi> as of <hi>Tongues,</hi> or <hi>Miracles,</hi> which kinde of <hi>gifts</hi> were in thoſe Primitive times conferred upon divers, and that ſometimes by <hi>Impoſition of hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Puto agi de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no linguarum. Grotius ad Text</note> (as I ſhall ſhew you anon) And ſo <hi>Grotius</hi> (as ſome others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, taken notice of by <hi>Aquinas</hi>) here looketh upon this gift. But that <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170143:6"/>was the owner of any ſuch <hi>gift,</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath not acquainted us; And if hee were, yet this cannot ſo properly bee ſaid to have been conferred upon him, by the <hi>laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> which being but <hi>ordinary hands,</hi> were not ſo fit for the conveying of <hi>extraordinary</hi> grace.</p>
            <p>Others (and that the generality) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it rather of an <hi>ordinary</hi> gift; yet with ſome difference. Some expounding it of a <hi>miniſterial gift,</hi> whereby he was fitted for the work of the miniſtery, to <hi>teach,</hi> and <hi>exhort,</hi> and <hi>rebuke,</hi> &amp;c. This (ſay they) was the <hi>gift which was in him,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Others of the <hi>Miniſterial Office and Function,</hi> with the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> belonging thereunto, ſo divers both anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and modern.</p>
            <p>Now to whether of theſe two to incline my ſelf, I am ſomewhat dubious. And therefore, that I may be ſure not to miſſe the ſenſe, I ſhall do what I ſuppoſe I ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fitly may (and what <hi>Aretius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aretius Loc. Com. de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum impoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Loc. <hi>65.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> officium ſcil. cum gratia buic officio &amp; muncri neceſſaria. C. A. Lapide ad Text.</note> and ſome others have done before mee) put them both together, hereby underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (to uſe his tearms) both <hi>Munus and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas,</hi> the Miniſterial <hi>office</hi> and <hi>ability:</hi> Both theſe wee finde ſometimes ſet forth by this word, called <hi>gifts;</hi> So the word is uſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Having then gifts</hi>] what <hi>gifts?</hi> why? <hi>whether propheſy, let us propheſy, or miniſtery, let us wait on our miniſtring</hi>]
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170143:6"/>(ſo it there followeth) by the one (as ſome conceive) denoting the <hi>gift</hi> of teaching by the other the office, both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>gifts.</hi> So again, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. It is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>that when he aſcended up on high, he gave gifts unto men</hi> (I confeſſe the word there is not the ſame, yet of the ſame import, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>dona, gifts</hi>) meaning thereby not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>miniſterial gifts;</hi> and <hi>abilities,</hi> but <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices</hi> alſo. So the eleventh verſe explains it <hi>[He gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not unſitly may both theſe being put together, bee thus called a <hi>gift.</hi> To the making of a thing to bee a <hi>gift,</hi> there are two things requiſite. It muſt be <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitum &amp; commodum,</hi> freely given, and ſomewhat that is worth the giving. And ſuch is the miniſterial office, being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſuitable <hi>qualifications;</hi> It is a gift <hi>freely given,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, freely given to the Church, and freely given to the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> on whom they are conferred; and that to the great benefit and advantage of the Church, the end thereof being <hi>for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, and the edifying of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt</hi> (as the Apoſtle there ſetteth it out, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12.) which if duly weighed, and ſeriouſſy conſidered, might ſerve to conciliate and gain more reſpect to this <hi>office,</hi> than at this day it meeteth with at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170143:7"/>many hands in the world. But I may not turn aſide.</p>
            <p>Wee have found out what <hi>gift</hi> this was. Come wee in the next place to take notice of the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>means</hi> whereby this gift was conferred upon (or rather conveyed to) <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy.</hi> Where wee ſhall firſt begin with that which was <hi>occaſionall [which was giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en thee by propheſy.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Where we muſt again make the like enquiry, what is hereby meant?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I finde divers Anſwers returned, divers ſenſes being put upon the word <hi>Propheſy.</hi> Some whereof (I confeſs) are ſcarce worth the taking notice of.<note place="margin">Prophetia eſt forma Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti Ordinis Lapid. ad Text.</note> As that of <hi>Lapide</hi> (for which yet hee alledgeth ſome of the learned, with whom himſelf chooſeth to concurre, who hereby under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, the <hi>myſtical words</hi> uſed in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, which he interpreteth to be the <hi>form</hi> in this <hi>Sacrament of order</hi> (as hee calleth it) as <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> is the <hi>matter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hec coactum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur, Lapid. ad Ibid.</note> And no better is that of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atablus</hi> (taken notice of, and cenſured by him) who here turns the particle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>per</hi> into <hi>ad, The Gift which thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Propheſy,</hi> that is, (ſaith hee) <hi>ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiam,</hi> to the end that thou maieſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy, teach, and inſtruct the people. Leaving theſe, more genuinely; Conſult wee the word. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>prophetia, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy,</hi> it properly ſignifieth a <hi>prediction.</hi> a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170143:7"/>foretelling of a thing to come, now this is twofold; <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary.</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>conjectural, extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, divine</hi> and <hi>infallible.</hi> Now of which of theſe ſhall wee underſtand the word in the Text? why, take it which way wee will, wee cannot take it amiſſe. Both theſe had paſſed upon this our <hi>Candidate, Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> before his ordination to the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p n="1">1 There was an <hi>ordinary Propheſy,</hi> and prediction concerning him, which was <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> and <hi>conjectural.</hi> His younger years had put forth many early <hi>buds</hi> and <hi>bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes;</hi> ſuch as gave all that knew him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable hopes of a plentiful <hi>aftercrop.</hi> They ſaw him to bee ſo qualified both with <hi>gifes</hi> and <hi>graces;</hi> Graces of <hi>ſanctification,</hi> and <hi>Gifts of edification,</hi> that they voted him fit for the miniſterial office, looking upon him as a very hopefull inſtrument, likely to do much ſervice in the Church of God. Thus was hee both thought and reported of by thoſe that knew him, ſo you finde it <hi>Act.</hi> 16.2. where you have this teſtimouy giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of him. <hi>Hee was well reported of by the brethren that were at</hi> Lyſtra <hi>and Iconium.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prophetiam bi accipio pro pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omine faeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci &amp; conjectura Aretius ad Loc.</note> Here was a <hi>conjectural propheſy</hi> which went of him: of which <hi>Aretius</hi> underſtandeth the Apoſtle (at leaſt in part) here to ſpeak.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But this was not all; Beſides this there was a propheſy of a higher nature,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170143:8"/>that had given Teſtimony concerning him; a <hi>divine propheſy.</hi> Of this ſpeaks this our Apoſtle himſelf, Chap. 1. verſ. 18. of this Epiſtle. <hi>This charge I commit unto thee, ſon Timothy, according to the Propheſies which went before of thee</hi>] meaning divine revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions inſpiring ſome of the Prophets of thoſe times, directing them to point out ſome choice and ſingular perſons for the work of the miniſtery. Thus was <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, with <hi>Barnabaas</hi> ſingled forth, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2. <hi>As they miniſtred unto the Lord, and fasted, the holy Ghoſt ſaid</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical inſpiration to ſome one, or more there preſent) <hi>Separate me Barnabas and Saul to the work of the Miniſtery</hi>] And in ſuch a way was <hi>Timothy</hi> here called forth to the undertaking of this his miniſterial of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; not onely by the common vote and approbation of thoſe to whom hee was known, but by a ſpecial direction from God, intimating and making known his mind and will concerning him.</p>
            <p>And this our Apoſtle here taketh notice of,<note place="margin">Meminit hujus Prophetiae Pauius tùm ad commendatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Timothei tùm ad ſui ex cuſationem, Eſti. ad loc. Hoc diſertè hic commemorare videtur Apoſtolus, ne remere juvenis ad Evangeliſtae munus aſcirus vidererur. Beza Annot. ad loc.</note> mentioning it as being both the <hi>occaſion</hi> of, and <hi>warrant</hi> for, <hi>Timothies ordination,</hi> and calling to that office; which hee doth the rather (as <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Estius</hi> note upon it)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170143:8"/>as for <hi>Timothies commendation,</hi> ſo for his own <hi>vindication,</hi> that none might cenſure him for what he had done, judging that he had done raſhly, and unwarrantably, in impoſing hands upon a perſon ſo young as <hi>Timothy</hi> was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> Wherein let <hi>Paul</hi> be propounded as a <hi>Pattern</hi> to all thoſe who ſhal at any time have any hand in this great and weighty buſineſſe of <hi>Ordination.</hi> Let them learn from him to bee cautious and wary on whom they lay on hands. <hi>Lay hands ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly on no man</hi> (it is <hi>Pauls</hi> charge to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. eſpecially, if they bee young. Let them ſee that they have good warrant for what they do.</p>
            <p>To which end let them have an eye to theſe two things, to this double <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt <hi>Humane,</hi> that they be ſuch perſons as are <hi>well reported</hi> of, by thoſe amongſt whom they live, and to whom they are known. This is one of the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters that the Apoſtle giveth of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> a Goſpel Miniſter, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7. Hee muſt bee one that hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a good Teſtimonial, a good report;</hi> yea <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of thoſe that are without,</hi> without the Church, no members of it, much more of them that are within, ſuch muſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of a meet Candidate bee, not onely <hi>unblameable,</hi> but <hi>laudable.</hi> And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170143:9"/>withall hee ought to be ſuch a one as upon whom a humane and <hi>conjectural propheſy</hi> hath paſſed, one whom others look upon for his parts and <hi>gifts,</hi> as a hopeful inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of doing ſervice in the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And beſides this humane, let them look for ſomewhat of a <hi>divine Teſtimony,</hi> though not in an extraordinary way, as <hi>Timothy</hi> had (that is not now to bee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) yet in an ordinary; that they be ſuch perſons as in whom, in the judgement of a well regulated charity, they themſelves may ſee ſomewhat of <hi>God,</hi> of his grace and ſpirit ſanctifying of them, and ſo fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them for this ſo weighty a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>And now, theſe two concurring, they may comfortably go on in ordaining and ſetting apart ſuch a one thereunto, which how it is to bee done, the next clauſe will inform you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery</hi>] Where again wee muſt make further enquiry; what is here meant by the <hi>Presbytery?</hi> what by <hi>Laying on of the hands of the Presbytery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. For the former, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hereby ſome would underſtand <hi>the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Presbyter.</hi> So <hi>Eraſmus</hi> here tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſates it, <hi>Authoritate ſacerdotis.</hi> To which ſenſe I finde (what I wonder at) Mr.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170143:9"/>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> here not wholly averſe, yea,<note place="margin">Omuibus expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, diverſum ſenſum non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le quadrare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor, ut ſit nomen officii. Calvin ad Text. Quod de Impoſitione ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii dicitur, non it a accipio quaſi Paulus de ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum collegi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loquatur, ſed hoc nomine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationem ipſam intelligo Calvin. Inſtit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Cap. <hi>3.</hi> Sect. <hi>16.</hi> Cameron Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in Mat. <hi>18.15.</hi>
               </note> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where wholly for it, but by the favour of ſo judicious an Expoſitor (then whom I know none more) we may take notice, firſt, that the word here uſed is never taken in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this ſenſe. Neither can it well bear it. True indeed (as the learned <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron</hi> notes upon it) were it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it might be ſo conſtrued, <hi>Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, the office,</hi> or <hi>dignity of a Presbyter,</hi> but not ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, If the word would bear it, yet the ſcope of the place will not. For ſhould we ſo read it, [<hi>with the laying on of the hands of the office</hi> (or <hi>dignity</hi>) <hi>of a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter</hi>] I muſt profeſſe (with the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour) I ſhould not know what ſenſe to make of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore letting that paſſe; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire we how this word is elſewhere uſed. That wee may ſoon ſee, there being but two other Texts where it is to bee found. The one <hi>Luke</hi> 22.66. where wee read of <hi>the Elders of the people;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The other <hi>Act.</hi> 22.5. where wee meet with <hi>the eſtate of the Elders,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; In both places thereby mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great <hi>Councel of the Sanhedrim, a Colledge</hi> or <hi>company of officers,</hi> to whom the Government of the Church was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Here is the Original, both of the name and thing, from whence it was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170143:10"/>derived (as moſt other things concerning Eccleſiaſtical Government were) unto the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> which in like manner had its <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> Societies, and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Church officers, to whom the Government of the Church was in like manner committed. And in this ſenſe (without queſtion) are wee to look upon the word here in the text, as denoting <hi>Caetum, ſeu Collegium Presbyterorum,</hi> a <hi>Company of Presbyters.</hi> Herein the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Expoſitors, both Ancient and Modern,<note place="margin">Presbyterium qui hic collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum nomen eſſe putant, pro Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum poſitum, recte ſentiunt meo judicio, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin ad Text.</note> both Proteſtant and Romiſh, do fully accord; Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo among the reſt (upon ſecond thoughts) yeilding his free aſſent thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Only the queſtion remains, what <hi>kinde of Presbyters</hi> were theſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this ſhall wee give the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Anſwer, moſt of them will round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell us, that they were <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Biſhops as diſtinct from <hi>Presbyters;</hi> wherein they plead the conſent of ſome of the Ancients. Such was the office (ſay they) to which <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordained, not of a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> but of a <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Now it was never the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome for <hi>Presbyters</hi> to ordain <hi>Biſhops.</hi> No, <hi>The leſſe is bleſſed of the better,</hi> (the <hi>greater</hi>) faith the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Prieſtly office) <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.7. Not the greater of the leſſe. <hi>Presbyters</hi> are ordained by <hi>Biſhops,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170143:10"/>not <hi>Biſhops</hi> by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> And herein we finde them ſeconded by ſome of our own of late times, who contend that the office to which <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordained, was the office of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> an <hi>Arch-Biſhop,</hi> a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane.</hi> And conſequently the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> here ſpoken of, muſt bee a company of <hi>Biſhops</hi> (at leaſt) not of ordinary <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In purſuit whereof, ſome there are who ſpare not to affirm, that in <hi>Pauls</hi> time there was no ſuch order in the Church. No <hi>Presbyters</hi> properly ſo called. True indeed in a large ſenſe (ſay they) the Apoſtles (ſome of them) ſometimes ſtile themſelves ſo, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> who write them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Presbyters;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. 2 <hi>Epiſt. Joh.</hi> 1. and 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. But ſtrictly and properly there was then none of this order. None at leaſt till St. <hi>Johns</hi> time, the laſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Then indeed (ſay they) was this <hi>order</hi> introduced as a middle office betwixt Biſhops and Deacons. But before that, there were no other ordinary offices in the Church, but theſe two, taking the word <hi>Biſhops,</hi> in a ſtrict acception; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the <hi>Presbytery</hi> here ſpoken of could bee no other. So high are ſome flowne in theſe diſtracted times; being (as they ſay) of ſome Meteors, ſet on fire by an <hi>Antipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtaſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as for this opinion, as it is but novel,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170143:11"/>newly hatched, and ſingular, ſo I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is not like to be long lived, it being ſuch as the beſt friends to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> (which the moderate party are) (I preſume) will not bee willing to own. Neither indeed is there any reaſon they ſhould, in as much as it runnes ſo directly croſſe; as to clear evidence of <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo to the general (if not univerſal) conſent of all divines both Ancient and Modern; who look upon the office of a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> as in <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> precedent to that of a <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Yea ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily preceding it, that who ever ſhall be ordained a <hi>Biſhop, per ſaltum,</hi> not having firſt a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> they pronounce his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination invalid, a meer nullity. So it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed both by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> &amp; <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Yea by the moderate on both theſe parts it is alſo yeilded, that <hi>Presbyiery is the higheſt order of ordinary Goſpel miniſtery. Epiſcopacy</hi> not being a different <hi>Order</hi> from it, but onely a different <hi>degree</hi> in the ſame <hi>Order</hi> a dignity conferred upon ſome one of the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and that for orders ſake, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent diviſion and confuſion.</p>
            <p>So then, leaving theſe forced ſenſes, take wee the word as it ſounds, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by it a Combination, or company of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> properly ſo called, ordinary Miniſters of the word, <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> ſuch as labored in the word and doctrin, whether the Miniſters <hi>of one Church</hi> or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170143:11"/>more; a <hi>Congregational</hi> or <hi>Claſſical</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery (as they are now diſtinguiſhed) is uncertain. M. <hi>Beza</hi> is for the former, nominating the place where <hi>Timothy</hi> was <hi>elected;</hi> and (as hee, ſuppoſeth) ordained,<note place="margin">Lyſtris aſcitum fuiſſe conſtat ex Act. 16.2. &amp;c. Beza. Gr. Anno. ad Loc.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Lyſtra;</hi> and that hee conceives by the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> the Miniſters of that Church; taking the conjecture from that forecited Text, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.2. whether ſo or no, as it is but conjectural, ſo is it not materiall. <hi>A company of Presbyters,</hi> there were which made up this <hi>Presbytery.</hi> And <hi>from</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>through</hi>) their <hi>hands</hi> did <hi>Timothy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this <hi>Gift.</hi> Sorunnes the Text, <hi>The Gift which was given thee by Propheſy, with the laying on of the Hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands,</hi> a Rite or Ceremony of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient uſe, and that in diverſe caſes. Four, or five of which wee meet with in the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> 1 In <hi>Benediction</hi> and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Thus the ſtory tells us, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14. how the Patriarch <hi>Jacob</hi> laid his hands upon the heads of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſe,</hi> which hee did for the bleſſing of them, as the 20 verſe explains the myſtery of it. 2 In <hi>Oblation,</hi> in offering ſacrifices to God. So you finde it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29. where <hi>Aaron</hi> and his <hi>Sonnes</hi> are ordered to lay their hands upon the head of the <hi>Bullock,</hi> which was to bee ſacrificed, verſ. 10.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170143:12"/>and ſo in like manner upon the two <hi>Rams</hi> verſ. 15.19. thereby dedicating and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating of them unto God. 3 In <hi>Atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in giving evidence againſt a Capital offender, of this you read <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.14. where the Law for puniſhing the <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> requires, that his accuſers ſhould lay their hands upon his head, for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their Teſtimony. 4. In <hi>Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Thus wee finde the <hi>Children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> (ſome chief among them in the name of the reſt) laying their hands upon the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> (which they did) not to <hi>ordain</hi> them to their office, no, that was done by <hi>Aaron,</hi> by whom they were <hi>offered up unto the Lord,</hi> (as the next verſe hath it) but that thereby they might declare and teſtify both their <hi>Reſignation</hi> and <hi>Approbation</hi> of them, how that they did for their parts, give up all the carnal and worldly intereſts which they had in them, and did approve of that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which was then to bee conferred upon them. 5 In <hi>Deſignation,</hi> in deſigning and appointing one to an office. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> deſigning <hi>Joſhua</hi> to bee his ſucceſſour; hee doth it with this Ceremony, <hi>by laying on his hands upon him,</hi> Numb. 27.18.</p>
            <p>Of ſuch uſe was this Rite under the old Teſtament, from whence it was transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the <hi>New,</hi> where we ſhall alſo finde it uſed in an equal number of Caſes. Firſt, In <hi>Benediction.</hi> Thus our Saviour is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170143:12"/>ſaid to have bleſſed thoſe children which were brought unto him, by <hi>putting his hands on them,</hi> Mark. 10.16. Secondly, In <hi>Miraculous operations,</hi> in healing of bodily diſeaſes. Thus our Saviour is ſaid to have wrought that cure upon that infirm woman <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.13. by <hi>laying his hands upon her.</hi> and the like power he gave to his Apoſtles, after his departure, as alſo to ſome others in thoſe primitive times. <hi>They ſhall lay their hands on the ſick, and they ſhall recover,</hi> Mark. 16.18. An experiment whereof <hi>Ananias</hi> made upon <hi>Saul,</hi> who recovered his ſight by his laying on his hands upon him, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.17. Thirdly, In <hi>Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Collations,</hi> in conveying of miraculous gifts. Thus did <hi>Saul</hi> alſo receive the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> (as it there followeth) And the like did many others, by laying on of the hands of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as you finde it in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter foregoing, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.18. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In that Apoſtolical inſtitution of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> (an <hi>Ordinance</hi> which the Church of God, after ſome foul depravations of it, hath now unhappily loſt, the reſtoring whereof according to the<note n="*" place="margin">Talem ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nuum impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem quae ſimpliciter loco benedictionis fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, laudo, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutam hodie in purum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum velim. Calv. Inſtit. lib. 4. Cap. 19</note> Primitive pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern is much to be deſired, as being very uſeful to the Church, and that as at all times, ſo eſpecially in theſe times where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into wee are fallen, whereof I have<note n="*" place="margin">Doctrin and Practice of Paedobatiſme, p. 76, 77, 78, 79 Printed Anno. 1645.</note> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where given a publick account to the world) of which, (after many of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170143:13"/>Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hic unus locus abunde te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatur hujus Ceremoniae origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fluxiſſe ab Apoſtolis Calv. Com. ad Loc. Piſcator Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius, Hemingius, Urſinus' D. Fulk, D. Willer, &amp;c. Vide <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I. H. B. N. Manuum impoſitionem cum Baptiſmo conjungit, quia ut duo erant Catechumenorum ordines, ita duplex erat Ceremonia, &amp;c. Vide Calvin, Com. ad. loc.</note> with diverſe others of our modern divines, eminent both for learning and pietie, do underſtand the Apoſtle to ſpeak, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. where among his <hi>ſix Principles</hi> of Chriſtian Religion, he reckons this for one, <hi>the laying on of hands;</hi> which being joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto Baptiſm, and coupled with it, it ſeemeth to import ſome reference and relation, that the one ſhould have to the other (as <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo obſerves upon it) and ſo cannot ſo fitly bee underſtood of any other thing as of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Children of Beleevers having been baptized in their Infancy, after that they had been competently inſtructed in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of that faith, whereinto they had been baptized, were confirmed by the <hi>Impoſition of hands,</hi> and ſo received for compleat mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church. Fifthly, and moſt uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Ordination</hi> of Church-officers. Thus did <hi>Timothy</hi> receive this <hi>Gift,</hi> his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial office, by, or with the <hi>Impoſition of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi>] a <hi>Myſtical Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> and that very ſignificative. Being uſed in <hi>ordination of Miniſters,</hi> diverſe things may bee conceived to bee repreſented and ſignified by it. Letting paſſe what the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170143:13"/>Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will tell us,<note place="margin">Hac impoſitione manuum ſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Eccleſiae, ut haec quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneatur, Deum per hanc per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam, &amp; ejus miniſterium; vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ipſos docere, &amp;c. Chemnit. loc. de Eccleſia. p. 159.</note> that hereby an <hi>indeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character</hi> is imprinted upon the perſon ordeined, and that <hi>Grace,</hi> yea <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia gratum faciens,</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by it,<note place="margin">Certe utile eſt ejuſmodi ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo cum miniſterii dignitatom populo commenſari, tum eum qui ordinatur admoneri, ipſum jam non eſſe ſui juris, ſed Deo &amp; Eccleſiae in ſervitutem addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. Calvin Inſtir. lib. 4. cap. 3. Sect. 16.</note> and that <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> ſo as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is hereby rendred the more acceptable unto God. Take what the true Churches of Chriſt hold forth unto us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereby it is <hi>declared,</hi> and that both publickly and ſolemnly, who they are that are ſet a part to the work of the Miniſtery; that ſo the people taking notice thereof may bee thereby induced to give ſuch reſpects unto them as belong to their office. To this end it is that civil <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> uſed to bee inſtalled with ſuch ſolemnities as they are; for the conciliating of reſpect from the people under their Government. And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a like account is this ſolemnity uſed in the Ordination of Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereby the perſons ordained are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated</hi> and <hi>conſecrated</hi> unto God, and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to his ſervice, even as the Sacrifices under the Law, by the ſame Ceremonie were ſet apart from a common to a ſacred uſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hereby a <hi>Gift is conveyed; viz.</hi> that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170143:14"/>
               <hi>Gift</hi> here ſpoken of in the Text. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Both the Miniſterial <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi> Both here ſaid to bee conveyed unto <hi>Timothy,</hi> by this means, <hi>by laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Not ſo</hi> (ſay ſome) <hi>this is more than the Text will avouch, which ſaith only, that this</hi> Gift <hi>was given him</hi> [with] <hi>the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of their hands, not</hi> [by] <hi>it. So they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between theſe two particles,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by <hi>and</hi> with. <hi>The former of which is here applyed to</hi> Propheſie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by Propheſie, <hi>the latter to the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with laying on,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But this is but a nice and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious criticiſme,<note place="margin">Compare Act. 13.17.14.27. &amp; 15.4. with verſ. 12. of that Chapter. Vide Bez. Gr. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. ad loc.</note> thus to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two particles, which are not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome indifferently uſed, the one put for the other (as it is obſerved by <hi>Beza</hi> and others) Letting go other Texts, conſult wee, but that one which is parallel to this, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. there wee ſhall find this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, turned into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtir up the Gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my hands,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> True (ſay they) <hi>Paul</hi> might ſay this of his hands, which had yet vertue in them to confer <hi>extraordinary gifts.</hi> But ſo have not the hands of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>extraordinary,</hi> or <hi>ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this let it bee anſwered, that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170143:14"/>though they have no ſuch vertue in them, yet they may bee imployed as <hi>inſtrumental,</hi> in conveying of what is not in their power to give. And this is all that wee intend when wee ſay that this <hi>Gift</hi> is conveyed by Miniſterial hands; wee do not ſay, <hi>confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> as attributing any proper Efficiencie to theſe hands, but only <hi>conveyed.</hi> Such is this Ceremonie of <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination; it is only a <hi>vehiculum, a moral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument,</hi> whereby this <hi>gift</hi> is conveyed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Office.</hi> Hereby the perſon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined is <hi>impowered</hi> for the exerciſe of his Miniſterial function, in diſpenſing of <hi>Word, Sacraments, Cenſures,</hi> all in an authoritative way. Even as <hi>Joſhua</hi> was inſtalled in his office by laying on of <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Office, ſo the <hi>Grace.</hi> This is alſo conveyed by this Ceremonie, where it is rightly uſed and received. So much our learned <hi>Cartwright</hi> ſticks not to grant to his Adverſaries of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> writing upon this Text. <hi>That Grace is given</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>by,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cartwright, Confut. of the Rhemiſts, in Text.</note> 
               <hi>and with the Ordination of Miniſters, when it is duly given, and received, wee willingly yeeld, becauſe the words of the Scripture bear it. Grace</hi> given in Ordination, and that by <hi>impoſition of hands,</hi> as hee there intends it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But what Grace? and how given?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer; <hi>Miniſterial Grace,</hi> ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to that ſacred function. This is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170143:15"/>given to the perſons thus ordeined, being ſuch as are fit for,<note place="margin">Haec impoſitio ſignificat col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae non quod Miniſtri dent gratiam, ſed quod ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant gratiam datam a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, Aquin. Com. ad Text. Cartwright. ib.</note> and do make a right uſe of this ordinance. <hi>Given</hi> to them, not by the <hi>opus operatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the work done, as if there were any ſuch intrinſecal vertue in this Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie. This wee renounce as a Popiſh dream, and that too groſs to bee owned by ſome of their Doctors. But only this is (as I ſaid) a <hi>vehiculum,</hi> an <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> and a <hi>means</hi> whereby this Grace is conveyed. So Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> there within a few lines ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains himſelf. <hi>It is a frantick device</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to imagin, that by the very work of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, grace is given, which is only the inſtrumental mean, whereby it is given.</hi> In ſuch a way it is, that <hi>Sacraments</hi> convey Grace; not by <hi>any Efficiency</hi> in themſelves, but only as <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> whereby the Spirit of God conferreth that Grace which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented aed ſignified by them. And in ſuch a way may this <hi>Grace</hi> bee ſaid to bee conveyed by <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> in this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Ordination. Whence it is that Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> (who is not wont to bee looſe and laviſh in his language, nor yet ready to gratifie his Adverſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impoſitionem manuum, qua Eccleſiae Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri in ſuum munus initiantur, ut non invitus patior vocari Sacram entum, ita inter ordinatia Sacramenta non numero. Calv. Inſt. lib. 4. cap. 14. Sect. 20. Supereſt impoſitio manuum, quam ut in veris legitimiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus Sacramentum eſſe concedo, &amp;c. Calv. ibid cap. 19. Sect 31.</note> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with them in any thing that may bee in the leaſt prejudicial to the Truth)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170143:15"/>declares himſelf, once and again, not to bee unwilling to indulge this Ceremony thus uſed, the name of a <hi>Sacrament. Non invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus patior vocaris Sacramentum.</hi> Not that he is willing to allow it a room among the ordinary <hi>Sacraments,</hi> which are ſeals of the Covenant of Grace, of which kind he owns only two. But in as much as herein it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles a Sacrament; it being by divine Ordination inſtrumental, as a <hi>morralſign</hi> in conveying Miniſteriall Grace, as the ſigns in the Sacraments are in conveying the Grace of the Covenant. So he.<note place="margin">Nec hic ritus eſt inane ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaculum, ſed cum precatio accedit, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tratur ſpiritus Sanctus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando, niſi ipſe ſit impius Hypocrira. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. Com. ad Text.</note> Wherein wee ſhall not finde him ſingular. Surely (ſaith <hi>Hemingius</hi>) <hi>this Ceremony of impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hands it is not inane spectaculum, a meer Pageant,</hi> to bee gazed and looked upon, but an operative ſign, <hi>which being</hi> (as it ever muſt bee) <hi>accompanied with prayer, now the Holy Ghost is hereby impetrated and obtained for the perſon or deined, unleſs hee bee one that is an Hypocrite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to him conſents <hi>Aretius,</hi> who alſo writing upon the Text, and taking notice how God was wont heretofore in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times to own this Ordinance of his, by giving ſome evidence that the perſon ſo ſet apart was well pleaſing to him, hee adds, <hi>Et indubiè,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Indubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſi i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſymbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum rire adminiſtraretur, adhuc hodie. in Electionibus non minus quam oli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n effet efficax, ſi max me externa &amp; inſolita ratione ſeſe non execeret ſpiritus Sanctus, Aret Com. ad Text.</note> 
               <hi>And without doubt</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170143:16"/>hee) <hi>If the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e rite were in a due manner ſtill abſerved in the Blection of Miniſters, it would bee found to bee no leſs effectual than hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; however the Holy Ghoſt may not ſhew himſelf in ſuch external operations, as then.</hi> Here is another uſe of this Rite, this Ceremony, and that a Principal one.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hereby a <hi>charge is impoſed.</hi> Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> laying his hands upon <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Illo ipſo etiam ritu tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m ſolemni voto &amp; obligatione, is qui vocatus eſt, obligatus cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deo, ſub teſtimonio Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ad eam fidelitatem in Miniſterio pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandam, quam Dominus in diſpenſationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 1 Cor. 4.2. Chemnit. Ioc. de Eccleſia. p. 137.</note> hee is ſaid <hi>to give him a charge before all the people,</hi> Numb. 27.23. And in like manner the Miniſters of God laying their hands upon the perſons ordained, they do thereby in the name of God impoſe a <hi>charge</hi> upon them, even the ſame that <hi>Paul</hi> doth here upon <hi>Timothy, not to neglect the gift</hi> which thereby they receive, but ſeriouſly with their <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> to intend that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration committed to them, leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the hand of the Lord go out againſt them, and fall heavy upon them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. (To name no more) Hereby a <hi>bleſſing is aſſured.</hi> A threefold bleſſing. Divine <hi>Protection, Direction, Aſſiſtance.</hi> Thus is the <hi>hand of the Lord</hi> ſaid to have been <hi>upon</hi> his ſervant <hi>Ezra, Ezra</hi> 7.6.9. <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the good hand of his God upon him,</hi> God was pleaſed to exerciſe a gracious providence towards and upon him, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting, directing and proſpering him in his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170143:16"/>undertakings. And thus ſhall the <hi>hand of the Lord</hi> bee upon his faithfull ſervants, his Miniſters, going about his work in his name; which is repreſented and aſſured to them by this Rite, this Ceremony in their Ordination, the <hi>laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ceremoniam pro ipſo actu Ordinationis poſuit. Calv. ad Text.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Of ſuch excellent uſe then is this <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony.</hi> And hence is it, that it is here as (elſewhere) put for the whole work of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</hi> Not but that therein there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actions of ſpecial import, ſuch are the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>prayer.</hi> The two ordinary means whereby <hi>every Creature of God is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,</hi> as our Apoſtle tells us in the fifth verſe of this Chapter. Sanctified in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way, ſo as they may bee comfortably uſed, with expectation of a bleſſing upon them. And by theſe means the perſons or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined come to bee <hi>ſanctified</hi> in a ſpecial manner, in a peculiar way; by the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>prayer,</hi> which are the <hi>eſſential parts</hi> of this Ordinance (as might bee ſhewed; if need were.) But in as much as this <hi>Ceremony</hi> is moſt obvious and obſervable to the eye, therefore the whole action taketh the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination from it, being called, <hi>the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I with what brevity might bee,<note place="margin">Applicat.</note> paraphraſed upon this former part of the Text. From whence I might now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, or rather take up divers doctrinal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170143:17"/>touching the buſineſs which wee are here met about this day, the <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Ordination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. So I call it (let that bee the firſt of them) and that not without good warrant from my Text, <hi>the Ordinance of Ordination.</hi> And that not a <hi>humane,</hi> but a <hi>divine</hi> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſo of perpetual uſe unto the Church of God; which were it but belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſurely it would not bee ſo ſleighted, as by many it is at this day. <hi>Pauls</hi> charge to <hi>Timothy</hi> here is, that hee ſhould not <hi>neglect the Gift</hi> which hee had received in, and by his Ordination. How is it that ſo many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us ſo ſleight this <hi>gift,</hi> as that they will not receive it in this way? No, if they have but a <hi>Call</hi> (as they call it) an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection</hi> by two or three, and can by any means procure a formal <hi>Approbation,</hi> or yet a <hi>Toleration;</hi> it is enough for them. A <hi>Gift</hi> they have already (at leaſt as they think) and they look out for no more. Now they let upon the work, and that not as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationers,</hi> for tryal ſake, in order to <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (which being done with the Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thoſe who have power to lay on hands, and that for ſome competent time, untill Ordination can bee obtained, I have nothing to ſay againſt it) but in a <hi>fixed way,</hi> as their ſetled imployment. Taking upon them not only to <hi>preach</hi> (which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly they cannot bee ſaid to do without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170143:17"/>Ordination; <hi>Teach</hi> they may, but <hi>preach</hi> they cannot. <hi>How ſhall they preach except they bee ſent?</hi> Rom. 10.15. Preach as <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, Officers,</hi> in an authoritative way; this they cannot do without an <hi>authoritative miſſion</hi>) but alſo to <hi>adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and that not only <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> (which upon what account I know not) hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore been looked upon as of an inferiour nature, and ſo permitted in ſome caſes to bee diſpenſed by ſecular hands) but alſo the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> wherein what do they but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Ordinances of God, and abuſe his people, gulling and deceiving them, by giving them ſhels for kernels, ſhadows for ſubſtances? So neceſſary is <hi>Ordination</hi> (I mean, for the ſubſtance of it) as that (in an ordinary way) none can perform any miniſterial act without it. But I muſt but touch upon things, only giving you a hint of what might have been inlarged.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place, as <hi>Ordination</hi> it ſelf is neceſſarie, ſo this <hi>Ceremony</hi> uſed in it, of <hi>impoſition of hands,</hi> is more than indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. Mark it, I do not ſay, <hi>abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,</hi> ſo eſſential unto this Ordinance, as that it ſhould bee null and void without it. I ſhall herein bee as tender as I may. But more than <hi>indifferent,</hi> an <hi>adjunct</hi> which ought not to bee ſevered from it. For this beſides the conſtant, and almoſt univerſal practice of the <hi>Church,</hi> in all times, in all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170143:18"/>places (which ought to bear more than a little ſway with thoſe that live in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and acknowledge themſelves mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it) <hi>Scripture evidence</hi> (mee thinks) ſhould bee clear and convincing enough. For <hi>practice,</hi> how is it that <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> though perſons extraordinarily quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and dignified, were thus ſet a part, by <hi>laying on of hands?</hi> Act. 13.3. And here <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> in like manner; And ſo all the Elders, the Miniſters of thoſe times; a thing ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that it cannot bee denyed. And whence is it that the whole <hi>action</hi> (as I have ſhewn you) was denominated from this <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony,</hi> commonly known by this name of <hi>impoſition of hands?</hi> a plain evidence that this was alwayes a part of it, never omitted.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Why? but it may bee ſaid, though wee have</hi> Preſident <hi>for it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Licet autem nullum extet certum precep tum de manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um impoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, quia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men fuiffe in perpetuo uſu Apoſtolis vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, illa tam acurata corum obſervatio prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis eſſe debet. Cal. Inſtit. l. 4. cap. 3. Sect. 16.</note> 
               <hi>yet no</hi> precept. <hi>So as though it may bee done, yet there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that it ſhould bee ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Suppoſe it that wee have not, yet (as <hi>Calvin</hi> concludes) inaſmuch as wee finde it in ſuch conſtant uſe among the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and their next ſucceſſors, their ſo exact obſerving of it, may well bee inſtead of a Precept unto us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, if wee have not an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> precept for it, yet an <hi>implicite</hi> one wee have, which is <hi>tantamount:</hi> what elſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> where hee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170143:18"/>chargeth him not to <hi>lay on hands ſuddenly,</hi> on any man; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 50.22. ſurely that <hi>Caution</hi> implyeth an <hi>injunction;</hi> whileſt he prohibits the manner, hee requireth the <hi>thing;</hi> whileſt hee forbids him to lay on hands <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> hee intimates it as his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do it <hi>regularly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it may bee ſaid. However this was then uſed, yet there is no neceſſity it ſhould now bee continued, in as much as this <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ny</hi> hath loſt the vertue which then it had. Even as it is with <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utream unction,</hi> the annointing of the ſick, it was then practiſed with an Apoſtolical warrant, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14. but having ſince loſt that effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy which then it had, it hath from thoſe times been laid aſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> But ſo hath not <hi>Impoſition of hands in Ordination,</hi> which that ever it was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous wee read not, however, not the laying on of the hands of the <hi>Presbytery.</hi> The ſame uſe which then it had, it ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, and ſo, as it hath been, ſo ſtill it ought to bee continued in the Church. But I come not here to diſpute this point,<note place="margin">Vide jus divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Miniſterii Evangelici Part 1. Cap. 12. and M. Laz. Seamans Anſwer to Chillenden. Hoe poſtremô habendum eſt, non univerſam multitudinem manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſſe ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maniſtris, ſed ſolos Paſtores. Calv. Inſtit. ubi ſupra.</note> which hath been ſufficiently done by the pens of others of late times. Paſſe wee on.</p>
            <p>In the third place; As hands are to bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170143:19"/>impoſed in Ordination, ſo ſee <hi>what</hi> or <hi>whoſe</hi> hands. Not the <hi>Peoples.</hi> They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed may with ſome colour lay claim to a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but not ſo to a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to a lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of their hands (as the manner anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently was,) in the <hi>electing</hi> or <hi>approving</hi> of their Miniſters, but not a <hi>laying on their hands</hi> in <hi>ordaining</hi> them. Surely as this findes no warrant from ſcripture, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it conſonant to <hi>Religion,</hi> or right <hi>reaſon,</hi> that they who are not inveſted with any ſuch power themſelves, ſhould derive it unto others, ſo giving that which they have not, whether formally or vertually. And if ſo, what needed <hi>Paul</hi> to have left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete</hi> to <hi>ordain Elders in every Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> (which he did, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.) if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might have done it? Surely this muſt be the <hi>Presbyters</hi> work.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And that not of one ſingle <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> however qualified, however digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Scripture ſpeaking of this <hi>Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> it ſtill ſpeaketh of <hi>hands</hi> in the plural number, not ſingular, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith the Text) <hi>The laying on of hands.</hi> And that not of one ſingle perſon, but more, not of one <hi>Presbyter,</hi> but of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery. Thus was <hi>Timothy</hi> here ordained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But here a ſtone lyeth in my way, which muſt bee removed; was not <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> ordained by <hi>Pauls hands,</hi> and his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? The Text is expreſſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170143:19"/>where giving him the like charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this <hi>gift,</hi> hee minds him that hee hath received it by the <hi>putting on of his hands.</hi> How then by the hands of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this it is anſwered by ſome, that the <hi>Gift</hi> there ſpoken of is not the ſame with this in the Text; but ſome <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous gift.</hi> So <hi>Diodate</hi> conceives of it.<note place="margin">Diodate in 2 Tim. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>It ſhould ſeem</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that by the Impoſition of Saint</hi> Pauls <hi>hands,</hi> Timothy <hi>received the miraculous gifts, and by the Impoſition of the Colledge of Elders hands, hee was inſtalled in the Miniſtery.</hi> But in as much as wee do not finde either from <hi>Scripture,</hi> or any ſure record of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> that <hi>Timothy</hi> had any ſuch miraculous gifts, therefore wee wave that conjecture.</p>
            <p n="2">2 More probably and genuinely; it is conceived by others, (and that by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Expoſitors) that <hi>Paul</hi> and the <hi>Presbytery</hi> did joyn in the ſame <hi>Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in ordaining <hi>Timothy</hi> to his Miniſterial office, they <hi>laid on hands together.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nullus eſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitandi locus quin Timothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us a ſeniorum collegio elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fuerit, qui toti Collegio praeeſſet. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron Praelect in Mat. 18. &amp; 15</note> Onely hee as a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>leader,</hi> and <hi>fore-man</hi> in that ſervice (which well hee might bee, being an extraordinary perſon) they joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him as ordinary officers. Thus did <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> afterwards ordaine, not alone, but with others, onely them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being as leaders in the work. A pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern which was afterwards followed by the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170143:20"/>Church,<note place="margin">Ex Dei ordinatione perpetua ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe fuit, eſt, &amp; erit, ut in Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterio quiſpiam &amp; loco, &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Primu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, actioni guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandae preſit. Beza de Miniſtr. Evang. Grad. Cap. 23. Tales Epiſcopos divinitus, &amp; quaſi ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Chriſti voce, conſtitutós, abſit ut unquam ſimus inficianti. Idem ibid. Cap. 21.</note> which in her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations was wont to have a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a <hi>Primus Presbyter,</hi> one <hi>firſt;</hi> (to whom after ages, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated the name of a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> which in the Apoſtles time was alike common to all <hi>Presbyters</hi>) who for orders ſake lead the way, having the firſt hand in ſervices of this nature. So as theſe two may well ſtand together. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> was ordained by the laying on of <hi>Pauls</hi> hands, and yet by the hands of the <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But here falls in a queſtion which ſome may think to bee pinching to us, who are here met together about this ſervice this day. Where there is not the ſame <hi>order</hi> obſerved, is the <hi>ordination</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid? May the <hi>Presbytery</hi> without ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without a <hi>Biſhop</hi> lay on hands?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Anſwer to this, I ſhall not much regard, either what they of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any over-heated ſpirits among our ſelves have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who in the <hi>want</hi> of this order, make a <hi>nullity</hi> of the <hi>Ordinance,</hi> pronounce the ordination invalid and void; by which harſh cenſure of theirs, what do they but moſt uncharitably; and even unchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, degrade, though not all, yet the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170143:20"/>greateſt, and moſt conſiderable part of the Miniſters of Chriſt, in the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches throughout the world, making them no <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and ſo <hi>unchurching</hi> their Churches. Leaving them.</p>
            <p>As for the more moderate ſpirits among our ſelves, (with whom I deſire onely to deal, and for whoſe ſakes it is that I ſpeak what I do) how ever they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this as the more regular way, more agreeable to the practice of Antiquity, and the Scripture pattern, yet they freely yeild it, that where this is not to bee had, where either there are no ſuch <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or thoſe not fit, or not willing to ordain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but of their own faction, themſelves being not <hi>Orthodox,</hi> or elſe (which is all one) not permitted to exerciſe that part, of their ſuppoſed Juriſdiction, now the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> ordinary Presbyters, may do it without them. So our eminently learned and judicious <hi>Davenant,</hi> lately a <hi>ſtar</hi> of the <hi>firſt magnitude</hi> in this our <hi>Horizon,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf alſo ſoon after a <hi>Biſhop</hi>) hath plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined it.<note place="margin">In Eccleſia turbata, ubi Epiſcopi omnes in haereſin aut Idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam inciderunt, &amp;c. ſi Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxi Presbyteri (ne pereat Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fia) alios Presbyteros cogantur ordinare, ego non auſim hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Ordinationes pronunciare irritos &amp; inanes. Davenant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termi. Queſt 42.</note> 
               <hi>In Eceleſiâ turbatâ &amp;c. In the troubled ſtate of the Church,</hi> where ordination cannot bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Epiſcopal hands, it both may and ought to be from the hands of <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170143:21"/>Presbyters.</hi> To which <hi>Armacham,</hi> (by him cited) in one caſe agrees, <hi>viz.</hi> when the Biſhops are all dead. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (what he there alſo taketh notice of) it is no leſſe than a wonder, that thoſe who in ſome caſes (in caſe of imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) will allow any private perſon, a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, or whoever) to <hi>baptiſe</hi> an Infant, (which by divine inſtitution belongs only unto Miniſters) and account it valid, yet will rather ſuffer the Church to go to wrack, and periſh, than to admit of <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> by the hands of <hi>Presbyters;</hi> which if rightly conſidered, and applyed to the preſent times, I preſume may bee ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſatisfy any ſuch well-adviſed and moderate ſpirits, as his was.</p>
            <p>To this I might adde what is taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by others, and that from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of ſome of thoſe who have appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for,<note place="margin">Vide jus divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Regim. Eccl. p. 132.</note> and pleaded the cauſe of <hi>Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> among our ſelves, who have freely and ingenuouſſy acknowledged, (what indeed cannot bee denied) that <hi>Presbyters</hi> as <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> are indued with an intrinſecal po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authority to ordain others, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been onely limited and reſtrained in the exerciſe of that power by the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church,</hi> for orders ſake; which <hi>Diſcipline</hi> being now in this Nation for the preſent (at leaſt) layed aſleep, it cannot bee thought any uſurpation in them, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170143:21"/>aſſume and exerciſe that power, which is confeſſedly intrinſecall to their order. But I have neither time, nor will, to wade into debates of this nature. I have done with <hi>Doctrinal informations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which, had I any time further to ſpend, I might now ſubjoyn ſome <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Applications,</hi> and that both to <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and <hi>people.</hi> 1 To <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſuch as <hi>would be,</hi> ſuch as <hi>are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Such as <hi>would</hi> bee, <hi>Candidates, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectants,</hi> ſuch as intend and deſire the work and office of the Miniſtery (which who ſo are in meaſure fitted for it, and have a ſincere intention of doing ſervice to God and his Church in it, without any Ambition may do, as our Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.) let them here ſee what <hi>door</hi> it is that they are to enter at, and ſee that they ENTER in by that door. Not tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them this <hi>office</hi> without a <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. No man taketh this honour unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not de <hi>facto;</hi> but de <hi>jure;</hi> not what men do, but ought to do,) not take upon them the miniſterial office without a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable <hi>Call</hi> thereunto; Which <hi>Call</hi> conſiſteth, not meerly in <hi>perſonal quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> or yet in a <hi>popular election,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in a <hi>Poteſtative miſſion,</hi> a <hi>Regular Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</hi> And let them enter in at this door, which the <hi>true Shepheard</hi> is ſaid to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170143:22"/>do, <hi>John</hi> 10.2. And who ſo doth not, hath a <hi>black Character</hi> ſet upon him in the verſe there foregoing.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For ſuch as are already <hi>entered</hi> in by this door, let them take up from what hath been ſpoken, both <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Counſel.</hi> Let this their <hi>Ordination</hi> which they have received, leave upon their hearts and ſpirits an <hi>indelible Character,</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally minding them, how they were thereby ſet apart, dedicated and conſecrated unto God for the ſervice of his Church. So as now they are no longer their own. <hi>Ye are not your own,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. much leſſe <hi>publick Officers, Magiſtrates: Miniſters,</hi> they are Gods and his peoples, not their own, ſpecially the latter, who with their own conſents are given up to the Lord, and his Church, and that for ever. Now being ſo, let them not live to themſelves. <hi>None of us liveth unto himſelf</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>But whether we live, wee live unto the Lord, Rom.</hi> 14.7, 8. And ſo let his <hi>Ministers</hi> live. Live to the honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Lord and Maſter, going about his work and ſervice in his name, and in his <hi>ſtrength.</hi> Not in confidence of their own <hi>Arm,</hi> but his; Which doing</p>
            <p n="2">2 Now let them <hi>comfort and incourage themſelves in the Lord their God,</hi> being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that ſo long as they are with him.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170143:22"/>hee will bee with them, his hand ſhall bee upon them. <hi>Thou haſt beſet mee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and behind, and laid thine hand upon me,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> ſpeaking of Gods providence towards himſelf,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.5. And thus ſhall the <hi>hand</hi> of God bee upon his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters; his <hi>good hand,</hi> his <hi>Right hand.</hi> That is the <hi>hand</hi> which is laid on in Ordination, the <hi>right hand.</hi> And this <hi>hand</hi> of God ſhall bee upon his Miniſters, being faithful in their Miniſtrations, now let them know, that hee hath <hi>laid his right hand upon them;</hi> which meditation may bee, and let it be uſefull to them in divers caſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To bear up their hearts and ſpirits againſt that <hi>mean eſteem</hi> which they meet withall in, and from the world. The world ſets them on the <hi>left hand; Wee are made as the filth of the world, and are the off-ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things even unto this day</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelf, and his fellow-labourers) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>ſweepage,</hi> and <hi>offall</hi> of the world. Such is the lot ſometimes, oft-times, of Gods faithfull Miniſters, though really ſuch as the world is not worthy of, yet they are meanly, if not baſely, eſteemed of, they are ſet on the <hi>left hand.</hi> But what of that? ſo long as they are, (which they are) <hi>the men of Gods right hand</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.17.) having his right hand laid on them. No ſmall honour. So it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170143:23"/>was to <hi>Ephraim;</hi> that hee being the <hi>yonger brother,</hi> his Grand-father <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould <hi>lay his right hand upon him,</hi> which the ſtory tells us hee did: and that wittingly, that he might put the more honour upon him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14. And ſo it is to the Miniſters of Chriſt, who for the moſt part are (as <hi>Ephraim</hi> was) <hi>yonger brethren</hi> (take it <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorically,</hi> or <hi>literally,</hi> it ſtill holdeth true) and ſo ſet (as <hi>Ephraim</hi> alſo there was, on <hi>Jacobs,</hi> verſ. 13.) on the worlds <hi>left hand,</hi> that God ſhould lay his <hi>right hand</hi> upon them, this is no ſmall honour, no mean dignity, ſufficient to countervail what ever contempt the ungratefull world can caſt upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againſt <hi>meanneſſe of eſtate.</hi> As for <hi>left hand bleſſings,</hi> worldly wealth, they have it may bee but a ſmall portion of it, in compariſon of others? Though it may bee they are not reduced to ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as <hi>Paul</hi> was; who tells us of his <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and <hi>thirſt,</hi> and <hi>cold;</hi> and <hi>nakedneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27. yet they are dieted with a mean and ſcanted competency, far inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to what others injoy. But what of this? Let it bee enough to them. the <hi>right hand</hi> of their God is upon them, aſſuring their intereſt in the beſt of bleſſings, which <hi>right hand bleſſings</hi> are.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againſt <hi>oppoſition, affronts, troubles, perſecutions,</hi> which they are ſubject to meet
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170143:23"/>withall, in and from the World. Theſe in ſome kinde, or other, they muſt make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of. But let them not bee diſanimated therby; <hi>let them in nothing fear their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> So long as the good hand, the <hi>right hand</hi> of their God is upon them, they are ſafe enough; that is a <hi>ſtrong hand. Thou haſt a mighty arme, ſtrong is thy hand, and high is thy right hand,</hi> Pſal. 89.13. This <hi>hand</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their <hi>heads,</hi> they ſhall need no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>helmet;</hi> this will bee to them a <hi>helmet of ſalvation.</hi> Only let it bee their care to do the work of the Lord faithfully, and then let them quietly repoſe themſelves under the covert of his <hi>hand,</hi> being aſſured of a gracious protection from that God, whom they ſerve in the Goſpel of his Son.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I might yet go on. Let this bee to them a <hi>Catholicon,</hi> a comfort and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in all their <hi>ſtraits,</hi> all their <hi>doubts</hi> and <hi>difficulties,</hi> when they know not what to do, which way to look, now let their <hi>eyes</hi> bee unto their <hi>God,</hi> whoſe <hi>hand</hi> is ſtill with them, <hi>If I take the wings of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and dwell in the uttermoſt part of the Sea, even there ſhall thy hand lead mee, and thy right hand ſhall hold mee,</hi> ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.8, 9. Such a gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence doth God exerciſe, as towards all his ſervants in general, ſo towards his <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> in ſpecial. In all places, in all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170143:24"/>hee will bee with them, to ſupport them; to conduct them. But I am ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A word for the <hi>people;</hi> and but a word. Let them <hi>own this Ordinance of God,</hi> and that by owning them that are put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. <hi>Wee beſeech you Brethren to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.) The <hi>Officers</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, ſuch as are ſet apart unto his ſervice, and come in his name, with his authority. <hi>Know</hi> them, and that ſo as to yeeld unto them ſuch reſpects as are due unto them upon that account. <hi>Eſteeming them very highly for their works ſake</hi> (as it there followeth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.) not grudging them that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>double honour,</hi> of <hi>Reverence,</hi> and <hi>mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> which our Apoſtle in this Epiſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voucheth the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, to bee worthy of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. with all, <hi>obeying them. Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſpeaking there not of <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> but of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſuch as <hi>watch for the ſouls</hi> of men (as it there followeth) <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. obey their <hi>Doctrin,</hi> and ſubmit to their <hi>Government,</hi> ſo far as they teach from God, and command for God. So doing, you ſhall not feel of that <hi>hand,</hi> which being laid upon them, is ready to go forth againſt thoſe, who will not hearken unto them.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170143:24"/>But I may not give way to further inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being alſo prevented in what I ſhould have done, in ſpeaking ſomewhat of the latter part of the Text; wherein wee have the <hi>matter</hi> of this <hi>charge,</hi> which wee meet with in the firſt word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neglect not]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In which word wee have a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, more intended than ſaid. <hi>Neglect not,</hi> that is, with care and conſcience attend thy miniſterial office, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out that Talent which God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto thee, ſtirring up the <hi>Gift</hi> which thou haſt received. So hee elſewhere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains and inforceth this charge, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>whereof I put thee in remembrance that thou ſtir up the gift of God, which is in thee</hi>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Metaphor taken from <hi>fire,</hi> which is ready to go out, unleſs it bee ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up. Even ſo are <hi>Miniſterial gifts,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they bee exerciſed. And therefore as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> under the Law had a care of that holy and heavenly fire upon the Altar, to preſerve and cheriſh it, by adding fewel to it, and ſtirring of it up; ſo ought <hi>Goſpel Miniſters</hi> to have of their <hi>gifts,</hi> which they have received from God, maintain &amp; che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them, ſeeking to increaſe them by the conſtant exerciſe of them, laying them out for the glory of God, &amp; good of his Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Appli.</hi> 1 A ſeaſonable <hi>charge</hi> for you (my Brethren) who are this day to enter upon this Miniſterial office; you are here to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170143:25"/>the like <hi>Gift</hi> that <hi>Timothy</hi> did, and that in the like way. Now to every of you bee this word ſpoken, and I wiſh it may bee ingraven upon each of your hearts, ſo as you may have it in a continual remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Neglect not this gift.</hi> You know how it fared with the <hi>ſervant</hi> in the Goſpel, who <hi>hid his Talent in a Napkin;</hi> It turned to a bad account to him in the end. And ſo will <hi>Gifts</hi> to their owners, where they are not improved. And therefore what you have received, or ſhall receive, ſee that you lay it out for your maſters ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, therein ſeeking the glory of God, and good of his Church. So doing, be you comfortably aſſured of what you have heard, that the good <hi>hand</hi> of your God ſhall be with you, and upon you, to <hi>protect, direct, aſſiſt, and bleſs</hi> you. Whereof take the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands</hi> this day as a pledge. But I ſhall not here anticipate what you ſhall anon receive more fully from another hand. To which referring you, beg wee a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God upon what hath been ſpoken.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:26"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:26"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:27"/>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170143:27"/>
            <head>AN Exhortation given to the late ordained Miniſters after the Ordination, in the cloſe of the day thereof, <hi>Norwich June</hi> 11. 1656.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no part of my task to intermeddle at all with any controverſies about the <hi>Ordination of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters:</hi> either to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the queſtion, of what neceſſity it is to bee an <hi>ordained Miniſter?</hi> or into that other, <hi>in whoſe power it is to ordain,</hi> and to whom properly it belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>This was the task of that Reverend Divine who preached the Sermon to you, who very dexterouſly and judiciouſly hath acquitted himſelf therein, mine is only to ſpeak to you who are now ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to put you in mind of your duty as ye are <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all which I ſhall ſpeak in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, both for the help of your memories
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170143:28"/>and mine own too, I will reduce to theſe three ſummary heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſhew you the <hi>great burthen of your Office,</hi> and what a weighty calling ye have taken upon you to diſcharge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To ſhew you the great peril and hazzard ye run, in the not diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it aright.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, On the contrary, the <hi>great reward</hi> which remains for every faithful Miniſter, for every one that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly and in ſome good meaſure diſchargeth it as he ought.</p>
            <p>And in inſtructing you herein, I deſire to inſtruct my ſelf, as being one of the ſame function with you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the <hi>burthen and weightineſſe of the Calling:</hi> when I conſider how <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and <hi>Jonah,</hi> Prophets all, ſufficiently and abundantly gifted, did ſo earneſtly decline it: and when I finde the great Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> accounting himſelf as <hi>inſufficient</hi> for the work of the Minitery: and not only the moſt fuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of the Apoſtles, but the moſt able alſo of all the ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> (great St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) ſhedding tears at the time of his Ordination, how can I, or any of you, but tremble at the burthen of it?</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Moſes,</hi> how unwilling hee was to undertake ſo great a burthen, doth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170143:28"/>many ways appear in Scripture, and that very remarkably: for when God called him to the office of a Prophet, and made choice of him to go unto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> wee ſhall finde him ſtrangely drawing back the ſhoulder more then once or twice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, At the very beginning, when God firſt ſpake unto him of it, Exo. 3.11. <hi>Come now therefore, and I will ſend thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Pharaoh, &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid unto God, who am I, that I ſhould go unto</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh? <hi>who am I,</hi> there is the firſt expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his unwillingneſſe unto it.</p>
            <p>Then again, after God had told him, that hee would certainly bee with him in the work, yet hee hath another excuſe for his backwardneſs; in the firſt verſ. of the next Chapter, Exod. 4.1. <hi>But behold they will not beleeve mee, for they will ſay, the Lord hath not appeared to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after God had provided againſt this excuſe alſo by three miraculous ſigns, which hee enabled him to perform, yet ſtill he draws back, and makes a new ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, hee pretends now that hee wants eloquence, verſ. 10. <hi>O my Lord, I am not Eloquent, neither heretofore, nor ſince thou haſt ſpoken unto thy ſervant: but I am ſlow of ſpeech, and of a ſlow tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea further, after God had ſtopt his mouth here alſo, telling him that he would be with his mouth, <hi>and teach him what he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170143:29"/>ſhould ſay,</hi> yet for all this, when hee ſaw none of his excuſes would hold, hee then in plain terms lays down his Commiſſion, and deſires God to ſend another in his ſtead, verſ. 13. <hi>And hee ſaid, O my Lord, ſend I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt ſend,</hi> that is, by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more fit than my ſelf, (as Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters expound it) ſo <hi>Calvin, Rivet,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Neither could God get him to go, till his anger was kindled againſt him, nor till hee provided a <hi>ſecond</hi> to go along with him, till hee told him his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhould go as an aſſiſtant with him in the work, as it is in the next verſ</p>
            <p>And that which aggravates all the reſt, is, that even before God called him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, there was no man fitter for ſo great a work, either in regard of all <hi>outward accompliſhments of body, or abilities of mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>outward bodily endowments,</hi> hee was <hi>a goodly child,</hi> as ſoon as ever hee was born <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.2. which though it bee but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely there expreſſed in the Hebrew Original, yet the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſufficiently explains it, when he ſtiles him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>proper Child, Heb.</hi> 11.23. Nay, St. <hi>Stephen</hi> goes further than the Apoſtle, and ſayes that hee was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170143:29"/>
               <hi>Divinely proper,</hi> or in a <hi>Divine manner fair:</hi> and therefore it is tranſlated in our Engliſh, <hi>Exceeding fair, Act.</hi> 7.20. which is an <hi>Hebraiſme,</hi> uſual in Scripture, that thoſe things which are excellent in their kind above the reſt, have the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thete of <hi>[Divine]</hi> added unto them: as the <hi>Cedars of God,</hi> and the <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of God,</hi> in the Pſalms, that is, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tall Cedars, and exceeding high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
            <p>And as in outward bodily endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hee excelled; ſo for <hi>abilities of mind,</hi> hee went beyond the reſt of his fellow brethren the Jews, as in <hi>all kind of humane learning,</hi> eſpecially in that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were eminent, having had his education <hi>in the King of Egypts Court,</hi> and that as the <hi>adopted Son of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs Daughters.</hi> St. <hi>Stephen</hi> hath a full and punctual place for this, Act. 7.22. <hi>And Moſes was learned in all the wiſdome of the Egyptians, and was mighty in words and in deeds.</hi> Yee hear hee was learned in all the wiſdome of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fitter to bee Gods Ambaſſadour unto them: yea and hee excelled in that very <hi>Eloquence</hi> whereof before hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained unto God, that he was defective, for hee was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith St. <hi>Stephen</hi> here) hee was <hi>mighty in words,</hi> as well as in <hi>deeds,</hi> hee was a powerful
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170143:30"/>ſpeaker. And yet for all this fitneſſe which was in him, no man fitter, you ſee how unwilling hee was to undertake this office, no man unwillinger: and therefore I have the longer inſiſted upon it, as being the notableſt inſtance which I meet withal.</p>
            <p>Neither was it ſo in <hi>Moſes</hi> alone, but in the next place in that other great <hi>Prophet,</hi> the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> ye may ſee a great backwardneſſe alſo to enter upon this fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.6. for after God had called him unto it in the verſe before, hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently crys out: <hi>Ah, Lord God! Behold I cannot ſpeak, for I am a child;</hi> he excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf too for want of <hi>Eloquence,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> did before, <hi>Behold I cannot ſpeak,</hi> (ſays hee) <hi>for I am a child!</hi> not as if hee were a child in <hi>age</hi> (Interpreters do not think ſo) but hee means it that hee was a child in <hi>knowledge</hi> and underſtanding, as the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſpeaks; and in regard of his unfitneſs to ſo weighty a function: ſo hee thinks of himſelf, and ſo hee undervalues himſelf, in his own opinion. And therefore in an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the unſupportableneſſe of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of it, hee cryes out with a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble voyce, <hi>Ah Lord God, behold I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeak! &amp;c.</hi> for the Hebrew word here uſed, is <hi>interjectio dolentis,</hi> an interjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of lamentation or groaning, tranſlated
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170143:30"/>elſewhere in Scripture, <hi>alas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet God did not call him from the <hi>Plow,</hi> as hee did the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> nor from the <hi>Herdmen,</hi> as hee did the Prophet <hi>Amos:</hi> Nor from the fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as hee did his <hi>Apoſtles, Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> for how much more then would hee have uttered ſuch words? but God calls him from among the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> from the Prieſts that were in <hi>Anathoth in the land of Benjamin,</hi> verſ. 1. where no doubt he had the education of a Scholler.</p>
            <p>And in the third place, as great a back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs was to be found in the Prophet <hi>Jonah:</hi> for though it was not upon his firſt call to bee a Prophet, as the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer were; yet upon his firſt call to bee a Prophet to the Heatheniſh <hi>Ninevites,</hi> hee ſhewed as ſtrange an averſneſs as either of the former, <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.3. for it was not onely a bare <hi>unwillingneſſe</hi> that appeared in him, nor onely a peremptory <hi>refuſal</hi> of it, but a direct <hi>flying</hi> from the preſence of God upon it, a quite forſaking of the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and going unto <hi>Tarſhiſh</hi> a ſtrange Country.</p>
            <p>Neither could God get him to go on his meſſage to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> till hee had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a ſecond call unto it, <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.1. and yee know how hee was fain to bee prepared too to the entertainment of that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170143:31"/>ſecond call, it was a bitter pill that hee was enforced to take for a <hi>preparative,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Phyſick</hi> would kindly work upon him, as the two firſt Chapters of his Propheſy ſhews: hee was fain to have a terrible ſtorm at Sea about his ears, the lot falls upon him to bee caſt overboard, to appeaſe it, a Whale comes and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows him up into her belly: and when he had been once throughly ſchooled for three dayes, and three nights, in the Whales belly, (in the <hi>belly of hell</hi> as himſelf calls it) then upon the Whales diſgorging of him upon dry land, he begins to liſten to the ſecond call of God, and not before.</p>
            <p>And as yee have thus ſeen it in three great <hi>Prophets,</hi> two whereof were two of the greateſt that ever were: ſo ye may behold it alſo, in the greateſt Apoſtle that ever was, even <hi>St. Paul</hi> himſelf: for was not hee brought up at the feet of a learned <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> that great <hi>Rabbi?</hi> doth hee not ſay of himſelf; that hee was not <hi>a whit behind the very chiefeſt Apoſtles?</hi> and that <hi>though hee was rude in ſpeech; yet not in knowledge,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.5, 6. nay hee was ſo farre from being rude in ſpeech too (though the falſe Apoſtles gave out ſo of him) that there is moſt admirable Eloquence in all his Epiſtles: which made that golden mouthed Father, St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> ſo to admire him, and which made
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170143:31"/>
               <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> put it for one of his three great wiſhes, that hee might but once have <hi>heard him preach out of a pulpit:</hi> and was hee not the great Doctor of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> deſtined peculiarly unto them above all the reſt of the Apoſtles? And yet for all theſe his great abilities, and great ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, ye may hear him crying out in his own name, and in the name of all the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel: <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> 2 Cor. 2.16. And if thou wert not, O holy and great Apoſtle, who ever was, or ſhall be ſufficient?</p>
            <p>And as the ableſt of all the Apoſtles felt his ſhoulders aking under the burden of it, ſo the greateſt of all the Ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> was as ſenſible of it, before hee entred upon it: even St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who hath been always accounted the moſt learned of all the Fathers. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> Church; and yet hee could not abſtain <hi>from weeping</hi> (as I ſaid before) <hi>at the time of his Ordination to the Miniſtery,</hi> out of an apprehenſion of the weightineſs of the function which hee was then to take upon him, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf writes in his Epiſtle to <hi>Valerius; Hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> erant lacrymae illae; quas me fundere in Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Ordinationis meae tempore nonnulli fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres animadverterunt.</hi> And when the ſame <hi>Valerius</hi> would have him become his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue and Copartner with him in his <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170143:32"/>office</hi> at <hi>Hippo,</hi> hee was ſo farre from an haſty accepting of it, that he weilds it off, and expoſtulates the matter with him, what hee meant to lay ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable burthen upon his ſhoulders, <hi>Jubes er go ut peream Pater Valeri? ubi eſt charitas tua?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I would wiſh all young Schollers and Students in Divinity, next unto the two Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and that to <hi>Titus,</hi> to read over this Epiſtle of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to <hi>Valerius:</hi> Where they ſhall finde how difficult a task the Miniſterial function is, and how unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that great <hi>Light of the Church</hi> was to undertake it.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe choice and pregnant inſtances, it will many other ways ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, what a <hi>weighty Calling</hi> the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery is, and how great the burden of it.</p>
            <p>True it is, that there are many <hi>honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble titles</hi> given to the Miniſters of God in Scripture: as that they are <hi>Men of God, Gods Embaſſadours, Gods Stewards:</hi> that they are <hi>Rulers, Elders, ſpiritual Fathers</hi> the <hi>Angels of the Churches,</hi> the <hi>Starres</hi> of the Churches, and the like: but all theſe do as well include their Duty as their <hi>dignity,</hi> and are as much for the <hi>Onus</hi> of the Miniſtery, as the <hi>Honos</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Is it not a weighty Calling that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſo much <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Knowledge,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170143:32"/>ſo much <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> ſo much labour and pains for to manage it; and that hath ſo many dangers attending it, and ſo many enemies to grapple with? Is not a <hi>cure of ſouls</hi> an heavy burden; I fear me, the heavieſt under heaven.</p>
            <p>Surely Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would never have written two large Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> upon this ſubject, if there had not been great need of a thorough inſtruction in this ſo weighty a function.</p>
            <p>For is it an eaſy matter to perform thoſe duties, which in thoſe Epiſtles hee enjoyns him, in the name of all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel? I will ſelect ſome of them for a taſte; as that 2 Tim. 2.15. <hi>Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God, a workman that needeth not be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of Truth.</hi> For though to ſtudy, to approve our ſelves to God, and to become workmen that need not to bee aſhamed, bee both of them duties of a very large extent: yet even that one alone, of <hi>rightly dividing the word of truth,</hi> what a great deal is there in it? for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rightly to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the word, is not ſo much to <hi>divide a Text,</hi> as wee uſe to ſay, but to give every one his portion of the Word ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as hee ſtands in need, <hi>Comfort</hi> to him to whom comfort belongs, <hi>Reproof</hi> to him to whom reproof belongs, <hi>convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170143:33"/>to him, to whom conviction belongs, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> to him, to whom inſtruction belongs, and the like: This is rightly to divide the word of God, and what a great deal of skill, and a great deal of wiſdome is there requiſite to the doing of it?</p>
            <p>Our Saviour himſelf tells us ſo in the parable in the Goſpel, Mat. 24.45. <hi>Who then is a faithful and wiſe ſervant, whom his Lord hath made Ruler over his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, to give them meat in due ſeaſon,</hi> or as St. <hi>Luke</hi> hath it more explicitly, <hi>to give them their portion of meat in due ſeaſon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is his word, every one his <hi>demenſum,</hi> that is moſt agreeable for him, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. ſuch a one muſt be a faithful and wiſe ſervant that can do this, ſaith our Saviour here, or a <hi>faithful and wiſe Steward,</hi> as he other Evangeliſt expreſſeth it.</p>
            <p>It is a point of wiſdome then, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires much dexterity, to know when to play the <hi>Boanerges,</hi> and when to play the <hi>Barnabas:</hi> when to be a <hi>Son of thunder,</hi> and when to be a ſon of Conſolation, when to thunder out the terrour of the Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men, and when to beſeech them in the mild and ſtill voyce of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: for both theſe muſt bee done by the miniſter of Gods word, but when and how to do them <hi>hic labor, hoc opus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170143:33"/>
            <p> Other places of the ſame Apoſtle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Timothy,</hi> I will but mention only, for brevity ſake, as that of his 2 Tim. 4.2. <hi>Preach the word; be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon: reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long-ſuffering and doctrin;</hi> That alſo of his 1 Tim. 4.16. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf, and to the doctrin; continue in them: for in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf, and them that hear thee.</hi> And what a great deal is there in either of both theſe?</p>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe in that which he hath unto <hi>Titus,</hi> Tit. 1.9. <hi>Holding faſt the faithful word as hee hath been taught, that hee may bee able by ſound doctrin, both to exhort, and to convince the gainſayers.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he may be able to confute the adverſaries, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal word properly ſignifies; now what a great deal of skil and ability is required to the doing of that, ye al eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: for every one that is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, is not preſently able to confute: and yet every Miniſter of the Goſpel ought as well to be able to confute, as to exhort; as hee ought to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo hee ought o bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: elſe what ſhould become of ſuch times as ours; wherein there is ſo much need of Confutation of all manner of errours and hereſies.</p>
            <p>Beſides the duty of Preaching, what a great deal of skill doth it require for to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170143:34"/>
               <hi>Catechize?</hi> what a great deal of dexterity to reſolve ſcruples and caſes of Conſcience? what a great deal of wiſdome and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to <hi>bind up broken hearts,</hi> and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirits? what a great deal of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to know the ſtate of the whole flock? and what a great deal of wary circumſpection in his carriage towards them all.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Catechizing,</hi> to lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion well, that requires a <hi>wiſe Maſter-builder,</hi> as the Apoſtle himſelf tells us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. And indeed the Maſter buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the reformed Churches, went this way to work at the firſt beginning of the reformation of Religion, which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with ſuch felicity of ſucceſs, that the <hi>Catechiſmes</hi> of the two chiefeſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the two great parties of proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants were accounted the uſefulleſt of all their other writings: for not onely great <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid it himſelf, that of all his own works none did pleaſe him but his <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm;</hi> and his book <hi>deſervo arbitro</hi> (as <hi>Sturmius</hi> relates that he read it in one of his Epiſtles:) but alſo great <hi>Calvins Catechiſm</hi> was inſo high eſteem in the Church of God, that it was thought worthy to bee tranſlated into all the three learned Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, both Hebrew, Greek, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine: <hi>Tremellius</hi> putting it into the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, and <hi>Henry Stephen</hi> into the Greek.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170143:34"/>
            <p> And herein the crafty Jeſuits have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to play the Apes of the Proteſtant writers, as in ſtudying the tongues, and many other things, ſo in this of <hi>Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing:</hi> they knowing full well the great neceſſity of it; and ſo may wee among our ſelves by the ignorant backſliding of ſo many from the truth in theſe days.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>reſolving caſes of conſcience,</hi> as it is a very neceſſary duty of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſo it needs a very skilful and able Divine: and though he Popiſh writers have herein got the ſtart of our Proteſtant Divines, they having been always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the greateſt <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> although with abundance of droſs in them; yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince that godly-learned man, Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> did ſet <hi>Caſe-Divinity</hi> on foot, by reſolving ſo many caſes of Conſcience, in his long continued preaching on that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, many eminent Divines have ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken themſelves unto it: as Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Rivet</hi> upon the Decalogue; and divers other in theſe dayes; Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> confeſſing that his hearing Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> preach thereupon when hee was a youth, made him ever after in love with that part of Divinity, in his preface to his Caſes of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the <hi>binding up of broken hearts,</hi> as it is a moſt ſoveraign part of the miniſterial office, ſo it requires a moſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170143:35"/>knowing and experimental Divine for to do it: a great deal of wiſdome alſo and diſcretion muſt bee uſed towards ſuch, and they are very tenderly to bee hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And as many worthy Miniſters are very excellent in this kind; ſo Reverend Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> had in his time a moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular faculty herein, whoſe works remain yet behind for us.</p>
            <p>And for the careful inſpection over the whole flock, the Miniſter as hee hath <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram animarum,</hi> ſo hee hath <hi>curam uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſcujuſque animae,</hi> hee hath the charge of every ſoul in his pariſh, and muſt give an account for every one that belongs to his charge: according to that of the Apoſtle; Heb. 13.17. <hi>They watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give account,</hi> &amp;c. Which inſpection over every one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular of the Flock, ſeems to bee intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that complaint which God makes of the <hi>Shepheards of Iſrael</hi> by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Ezek. 33.4. <hi>The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthened, neither have ye healed that which was ſick, neither have yee bound up that which was broken, neither have yee brought agian that which was driven away, neither have yee ſought that which was loſt, &amp;c.</hi> Now how great and weighty a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then this is, and what a diſcerning ſpirit it requires in a Miniſter, every one may eaſily perceive; it is indeed the right <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170143:35"/>part</hi> of every Miniſters office, as the Original word properly imports e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this <hi>overſight</hi> over the whole flock, ſo as to take care of every one of them as much as may bee: according as St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath it to the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Act. 20.28. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the flock over which the. Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo the Greek runnes. And as well St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.2. <hi>The Elders which are among you, I exhort: feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>Hath hee not the <hi>ſick to viſit,</hi> the <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to inſtruct,</hi> the <hi>unruly to admoniſh</hi> the <hi>feeble minded to comfort,</hi> and theſe as well privately, and from houſe to houſe, as publikely: agreeable to that notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 20.20. <hi>I have ſhewed you, and have taught you publikely, and from houſe to houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And adde to all theſe; what an <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary pattern</hi> he ought to be to the whole flock, and how unblameable in his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to them all: how he ought to preach unto them by his <hi>gracious life,</hi> as well as by his <hi>zealous doctrin:</hi> according to that obſervable paſſage of st. <hi>Jerom,</hi> in an Epiſtle of his to <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>biola, Tanta debet effe eruditio Miniſtri Dei, ut et greſſus ejus,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170143:36"/>et motus, et univerſa vocal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſint; ut quicquid agit, quicquid loquitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſit doctrina populo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> in one word that in every thing which he doth he may alwayes teach thereby. Which is no more than what both St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> give in charge to Miniſters: St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.12. <hi>Bee thou an example of the Beleevers, in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>titus,</hi> Tit. 2.7. <hi>In all things ſhewing thy ſelf a pattern of good works.</hi> And as well St. <hi>Peter</hi> as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.3. <hi>Neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> being Lords over Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing more there is, which I count none of the ſmalleſt part of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial burthen, eſpecially in theſe times of ours: and that is, the <hi>Adminiſtration of the Sacraments;</hi> for though I bee no patron of <hi>mixt communions</hi> (as they call them) or a promiſcuous reception of all ſorts, unto the holy Sacrament of the Lords ſupper, whether they bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or ſcandalous: yet ſeeing every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, as hee is called a <hi>Miniſter of the Word and Sacraments,</hi> ſo it is his duty to do both: mee thinks all the wiſdome and diſcretion that can be, ſhould be uſed by him, rather than wholly to fail of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting this main branch of his office; Doubtleſſe he ought as to be very conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiouſly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170143:36"/>prudent, ſo to be very prudently conſcientious in this matter.</p>
            <p>And ſo much the rather, becauſe it hath been alwayes the devils main po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, to caſt in a bone of contention into the Church of God, about this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Sacrament;</hi> as appeared firſt by the <hi>Papiſts Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the <hi>Lutherans Conſubſtantiation,</hi> and now in our days, by this ſo much controverted point of <hi>mixt Communions:</hi> by all which the Church hath been ſo rent and divided; as by nothing more; as <hi>Lavater</hi> in that excellent peece of his, <hi>Hiſtoria Saeramentaria</hi> hath evidently ſhown, that old wily Serpent, making that to bee the greateſt cauſe of diviſion among Chriſtians, which ought to be the greateſt cauſe of union among them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 Cor. 10.17. <hi>Wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many are one bread and one body, for we are all partakers of that one bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it requires ſo much skill, and ſo much prudence to manage well the function of the Miniſtery: ſo in the next place is it not a work of much labour too, and great pains? ſurely it muſt be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laborious work, when in Scripture the Miniſters of God are compared to <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandem,</hi> to <hi>builders,</hi> to <hi>harveſt-labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> to <hi>Shepheards,</hi> to <hi>Watchmen,</hi> to <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,</hi> to <hi>Nurſes,</hi> and the like. To hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170143:37"/>and builders, yee may ſee them both in one verſe, 1 Cor. 3.9. <hi>Wee are labourers together with God, ye are Gods husbandry, yee are Gods building.</hi> To harveſt-Labourers, that yee have in the Goſpel, Mat. 9.38. <hi>Pray yee therefore the Lord of the harveſt, that he would ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt.</hi> To ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, Ezek. 34.2. <hi>Sonne of man, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy againſt the Shepheards of Iſrael.</hi> To Watchmen, Ezek. 33.7. <hi>Sonne of man, I have ſet thee a watchman unto the houſe of</hi> Iſrael. To Souldiers, ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.3. <hi>Thou therefore indure hardneſs, as a good ſouldiers of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To <hi>Nurſes,</hi> ſo hee ſpeaks of himſelf, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>We were gentle among you, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a Nurſe cheriſheth her children.</hi> All which are no ſmall laborious works.</p>
            <p>And in the laſt place, as for the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that attend this weighty calling of the Miniſtery, and the enemies they have to grapple with, they are very many and great; for there is no kinde of men whatſoever, that have more oppoſition uſually againſt them, than the faithfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Word, they are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Mark</hi> at which both the <hi>Devil</hi> and the world do eſpecially aim; indeed both Devil and world do ſtrike at all good men, at all that carry the Image of God about them: but moſt eſpecially at the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170143:37"/>faithfull Diſpenſers of Gods word, their greateſt rage have been always againſt them: they know full well that to bee true of all faithful Paſtors, which was propheſyed of Chriſt the chief Shepheard, Zach. 13.17. <hi>Smite the Shepheard, and the ſheep ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Devil,</hi> hee rageth againſt the Miniſters of God above all other men, becauſe hee knows they give the greateſt blow to him, and are the greateſt pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers down of his Kingdome: and therefore yee ſhall find him ſtanding at the very elbow of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the high prieſt to reſiſt him, when hee went about ſo good a work as the rebuilding of the Temple, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yee know our Saviour told St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that the Devil had a mind to <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now him as Wheat:</hi> and not him only, but the reſt of the twelve Apoſtles: for ſo the words run in the plural number, Luk. 22.31. Simon, Simon, <hi>Behold Satan hath deſired to have you, that hee may ſift you as wheat:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtle, St. <hi>Paul</hi> too, who was none of the twelves, hee tells us of a meſſenger of Satan to <hi>buffet</hi> him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. and more expreſly, that hee was hindred by him more than once from comming to preach to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.18.</p>
            <p>Nay yee know hee was not afraid to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170143:38"/>upon Chriſt himſelf, who was the great Prophet of his Church; and the Prince of Paſtors; for hee was no ſooner baptized and initiated into his prophetical office by a voyce from heaven, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son hear him,</hi> but preſently hee was <hi>led up into the wilderneſs to bee tempted of the devil,</hi> Mat. 4.1.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how the Devils greateſt malice is always againſt the <hi>faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of the word, becauſe it makes his Kingdome to fall down; according to that ſaying of our Saviour to his ſeventy Diſciples, whom he ſent abroad to preach: <hi>I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heaven,</hi> Luk. 10.18. down falls he when the word is powerfully preached, as iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Calvin</hi> hath very excellently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded that place.</p>
            <p>And as Gods Prophets and Miniſters have the <hi>Devil</hi> moſt raging againſt them, ſo doth the world moſt rage againſt them too, the men of the world ſet themſelves againſt them on all hands.</p>
            <p>That it was ſo in the time of the <hi>Old Prophets,</hi> yee have it out of Chriſts own mouth, Mat. 23.37. <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt them which are ſent unto thee.</hi> Yea St. <hi>Stephen</hi> tells them, which of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have not your Father perſecuted? <hi>Act.</hi> 7.52.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170143:38"/>
            <p> And ſo it was with the Apoſtles after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and other <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> of the Evangelical Church, as well as of the Jewiſh, the world have always been about their ears: according as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us what fightings hee had with them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5. and therefore he bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Tymothy,</hi> in the name of all Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: <hi>Fight the good fight of Faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.12.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon of it, is the very ſame which our Saviour gives, why the world ſo extreamly hated him, Joh. 7.7. <hi>The world cannot hate you</hi> (ſaith hee to his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred) <hi>but me, it haterh, becauſe I teſtify of it, that the works thereof are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is the reaſon then, why the world ſo hated him and all his faithful Miniſters ſince, it is becauſe they reprove vice in them, men cannot indure to bee told of their faults. <hi>They hate him that rebuketh in the gate,</hi> Amos 5.10. for that was the place where the Prophets uſed to denounce woes.</p>
            <p>Now it is the very office of the bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> in the mouths of his Miniſters, to <hi>reprove the world:</hi> as Chriſt himſelf ſays of him John, 6.8. <hi>When hee is come, hee will reprove the Wir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> &amp;c. There is no zealous preacher that comes in the <hi>Spirit and Power of</hi> Elias, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did, but hee hath the many neaded <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170143:39"/>of ſinne to conflict withall: and the more zealous hee is againſt it, the more doth the world hate him, the more enemys doth he get amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Do yee not think that wee are like to have oppoſition enough on all hands, when wee have both the opinions of men, and the vices of men, to ſpeak againſt, both errours in Doctrin, and errours in life to deal withall.</p>
            <p>There are ever and anon <hi>errours</hi> and <hi>hereſies</hi> ſpringing up in the Church, but eſpecially in theſe our days, how many ſtrange and <hi>prodigious opinions,</hi> have been broached among us, all which wee that are Miniſters muſt oppoſe, it is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to <hi>defend the Truth,</hi> againſt all encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing errour whatſoever; wee above all others muſt <hi>earneſtly contend for the Faith which was once delivered unto the Saints,</hi> as St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks, for it is that which is committed to our keeping, wee are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with it by God: according to that of the great Apoſtle unto his <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and it is the very farewell clauſe of his whole Epiſtle, 1 Tim. 6.20. <hi>O Timothy, Keep that which is committed to thy truſt;</hi> and that is the <hi>pretious treaſure of truth,</hi> as both the context ſhews it, and Expoſitours interpret it: <hi>Cuſtodi Depoſitum, id eſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um veritatis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how many hornets then muſt the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170143:39"/>Miniſter needs have about his ears, who ſtands out at the ſtaves end againſt the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the times, hee ſhall have a load of malice, and a load of defamation, and a load of undermining, laid upon him from them that be contrary minded.</p>
            <p>And do yet think hee can expect leſſe, when hee comes to reprove the ſinnes of the time, and to tell men of their faults, O no! they cannot indure to have their beloved ſinnes medled withal, to have their boſome ſinnes touched: that is, to touch the ſore place, men kick and fling when the Miniſter comes to that. <hi>Herod</hi> was delighted with <hi>Johns</hi> preaching for a while, hee <hi>heard him gladly,</hi> Mark. 6.20. but no ſooner doth hee meddle with his <hi>Herodias,</hi> his darling ſinne, but off goes his head.</p>
            <p>Now every faithfull and zealous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter knows hee cannot diſcharge a good Conſcience, unleſſe hee boldly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially reprove ſinne in men, hee ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe bee guilty of their bloud, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 338. and therefore hee does his duty, though hee procures himſelf never ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enemies by it and never ſo much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger follow upon it.</p>
            <p>And thus ye have the firſt general <hi>head</hi> ſomewhat largely inſiſted upon to ſhew you what a <hi>weighty Calling</hi> it is to bee a <hi>Miniſter.</hi> I ſhall be briefer in the other two.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170143:40"/>
            <p> The Second general <hi>Head</hi> which I propounded to you, was the great perill and hazzard yee runne, in the <hi>negligent performance</hi> and undue execution of this ſo high and weighty a function, and that will appear. in theſe two main branches: Firſt, The <hi>Wrong</hi> which therein you do unto your <hi>ſelves:</hi> And then the wrong ye do to others, to thoſe that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your charge.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Wrong</hi> which hereby ye procurd to <hi>Your ſelves;</hi> it is not ſmall. Ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>unſavoureſt falt of the earth, fit for nothing but the Dunghill,</hi> which is our Saviours own expreſſion,Mat. 5.13. <hi>Ye are the ſalt of the earth: but if the Salt hath loſt his favour, wherewith ſhall it be ſalted? it is thenceforth good for nothing, but to be caſt out, and to be troden under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when God <hi>begins to enquire</hi> into ſuch unlavoury Salt, <hi>hee doth not eaſily make an end,</hi> as theſe dayes of ours are a ſufficient evidence of it, according as hee ſays by his Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> of the Prieſts of thoſe times, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2.9. <hi>I have made you contemptible and buſe before all the people, according as yee have not kept my wayes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, God doth uſe to take away the gifts of ſuch Miniſters and deprive them of thoſe excellent endowments of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170143:40"/>mind, with which hee had richly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, ſo that afterwards they become men of no eſteem for their parts: he <hi>takes away their talent</hi> from them which was <hi>wrapt up in a Napkin, or hid in the earth,</hi> as it is in the Goſpel, Mat. 25.28. <hi>Take therefore the talent from him,</hi> for <hi>uſe limbs and have limbs,</hi> as wee uſe to ſay: ſo, uſe gifts, and have them: uſe gifts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them: <hi>Habe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i dabitur, to him that hath ſhall be given,</hi> as it follows in the next verſ.</p>
            <p>But that which is the main of all, ſuch Miniſters endanger theirown fouls, and runne the hazzard of loſing everlaſting ſalvation: and what a pittiful thing it is that any of us whoſe office it is to convert mens ſouls, and to ſave the ſouls of others, ſhould fall ſhort of ſaving our own ſouls; that <hi>Judas</hi> who had once a place among the number of the twelve Apoſtles, muſt yet at length go to his own place in hell, as it is, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.25. <hi>From which</hi> Judas <hi>by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion fell, that he might go to his own place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I will not enter into that needleſs queſtion, <hi>whether on unconverted Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter can convert ſouls, or no,</hi> though I know nothing againſt it in ſcripture.</p>
            <p>And yet this is not all, for ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters do not only endanger their own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but they ſhall have an heavier pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of damnation than others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170143:41"/>ſuch men as knew their Maſters Will more: as our Saviour informs us, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47. <hi>That ſervant which knew his Lords will, and did not according to it, ſhall bee beaten with many ſtripes;</hi> for hee ſpeaks there of that <hi>faithful and wiſe Steward, whom his Lord ſhall make Ruler over his houſhold,</hi> as appears out of verſ. 42. and thoſe Stewards are his Miniſters, in the judgement of the beſt Expoſitors.</p>
            <p>And as yee ſhall thus wrong your ſelves, if yee bee not faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel: ſo in the ſecond place ſhall yee alſo wrong others, in no ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, even thoſe that are under your charge and to whomſoever yee relate as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p>For inſtead of converting ſouls, ye will pervert them, inſtead of indeavouring the ſalvation of others, yee will as much as in you lie procure their damnation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſtarving their ſouls in a negligent feeding of them, or by <hi>infecting</hi> their ſouls with unwholeſome and corrupt food, or elſe <hi>adificando in gehennam,</hi> by building them up into hell through an evil example and vitious life: when that is built up with one hand, is pulled down with another.</p>
            <p>And what a fearful ſinne is it to bee <hi>guilty of the bloud of ſouls,</hi> as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf calls it by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel? His bloud will I require at thine hands,</hi> Ezek.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170143:41"/>33.8. and yet how many ways may a Miniſter bee acceſſary to this Soul-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>If <hi>David</hi> ſo earneſtly prayed, <hi>Deliver mee from bloud-guiltineſſe, O God,</hi> Pſal. 51.14. how much more ſhould every good Miniſter pray againſt this worſt of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? for if God uſeth to make ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition after bodily murther, which is the leſſer, and ſo ſeverely puniſheth it: then much more will hee do it after the other, which is the greater, even the <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely an evil and unfaithful Miniſter is one of the greateſt partakers of other mens ſinnes, of any rank of men, and hath herein the greater account to give unto God: ſo that not without great cauſe did that good man pray, <hi>Lord forgive mee my other mens ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus yee have the ſecond general <hi>Head</hi> more briefly diſpatched; to ſhew you the great peril and hazzard yee runne, if yee do not faithfully diſcharge ſuch a weighty Calling as this is which yee have undertaken.</p>
            <p>The Third and Laſt general <hi>Head</hi> remains yet behind, and that is the great reward, which yee may expect, upon the faithfull diſcharge of your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial-office; which though the <hi>ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful world</hi> ſhould deny you, yet yee ſhould
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170143:42"/>bee ſure to receive it at the hands of God: and that both here in this life, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the life to come.</p>
            <p>And for the faithful Miniſters reward here in this life.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Yee have the <hi>Promiſe of Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> that hee will bee with you in the work, and will help to bear the burthen with you: which is the Concluſion of all St. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel, in the laſt verſe of it: <hi>Go ye and teach all Nations, &amp;c. and loe I am with you alwayes, even unto the end of the world;</hi> Chriſt ſays, hee will bee with them even unto the end of the world: and therefore it muſt bee meant of all the faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel, while the world ſhall ſtand, for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were not to live to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>And as yee have the promiſe of his aſſiſtance to help you forward in the work, which many a faithful Miniſter hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally often found, beyond expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſo in the next place ye have the promiſe of his protection alſo, to uphold and defend you againſt all the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries that yee ſhall meet withal in your Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>For hee it is that <hi>holdeth the ſeven stars in his right hand.</hi> Rev. 1.16. that is the ſeven <hi>Angels</hi> of the ſeven <hi>Churches,</hi> which are the Miniſters of them, verſ. 20. Chriſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170143:42"/>holdeth them faſt in his right hand, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſition either of world or Devil againſt them. And hereupon hee ſo incourageth his Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> in that very obſervable place, Jer. 1.18, 19 <hi>Behold, I have made thee this day a defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced City, and an iron pillar, and brazen walls againſt the whole land; and they ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt thee for I am with thee, ſaith the Lord, to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er thee.</hi> And the like encouragement doth hee give to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> againſt all the oppoſition which hee ſhould meet withall in the City of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> Act. 18.9.10. <hi>Bee not afraid, but ſpeak, and hold not thy peace, for I am with thee, and no man ſhall ſet on thee to hurt thee, for I have much people in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, hee hath declared unto you in his word, how ill he takes it at the hands of them that ſhall in any kind wrong you, or miſuſe you, yea or that ſhall not give that reſpect or eſteem which is due unto you, Luk. 10.16. <hi>Hee that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth mee: and hee that deſpiſeth mee, deſpiſeth him that ſent mee.</hi> But for thoſe that harm and injure you, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as enemies againſt you, there is a moſt formidable place of Scripture for them, which I can never read without ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious muſing on it, and gaining encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170143:43"/>from it in no ſmall degree: it is a direful imprecation by way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Deut. 33.11. <hi>And of</hi> Levi <hi>hee ſaid: Bleſſe Lord his ſubſtance, and accept the work of his hands: ſmite thorough the loins of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as he declares how he ill takes it at the hands of ſuch as ſhall wrong you and diſreſpect you, ſo on the contrary, how well hee takes any kindneſs done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Mat. 10.41, 42. <hi>Hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth you, receiveth me: hee that receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall receive a Prophets reward: And whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall give to drink unto one of theſe little ones, a cup of cold water only in the name of a Diſciple, hee ſhall in no wiſe looſe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> And this did clearly appear in the good <hi>Shunamitiſh woman,</hi> who ſhewed ſo much kindneſs to the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> as to provide all things needful for his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment as often as hee paſſed by her houſe, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.10. for God rewarded her with a Sonne being childleſſe, verſ. 16. and him <hi>raiſed to life again,</hi> when he was dead verſ. 35.</p>
            <p>And though theſe rewards from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out were not, yet the ſweet inward <hi>peace and comfort</hi> which ariſeth to a mans ſelf, out of a conſciouſneſſe of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170143:43"/>ſincerity of his faithfull diſcharging of the Miniſtery, this alone were reward enough here below.</p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place, the reward which you ſhall receive hereafter in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, the reward in heaven which remains for every faithful Miniſter, that no doubt is exceeding great, and ſuch as may throughly encourage you, and prick you forward to the work.</p>
            <p>For though wee do not peremptorily determine with the School-men among the Papiſts, that there are ſeveral <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olae,</hi> as they call them, ſeveral diſtinct Crowns of glory, for ſeveral ranks of Saints in heaven: as one for <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for <hi>Prophets,</hi> another for <hi>Martyrs</hi> and the like, among which they fooliſhly reckon one for <hi>Virgins</hi> too: yet as we have ſufficient ground in Scripture for ſeveral <hi>degrees of glory</hi> in heaven, ſo we have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough there for our encouragement, that the faithful Paſtors of Gods Church will be more than ordinarily rewarded for their labour in the kingdome of heaven.</p>
            <p>For beſides our bleſſed Saviours <hi>Euge</hi> in the Goſpel: <hi>Well done thou good and faithful ſervant, thou haſt been faithfull over a few things, I will make thee ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many things: enter thou into the joy of thy Lord,</hi> Mat. 25.21. Beſides this, we have a more expreſſe place in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170143:44"/>of <hi>Daniel;</hi> Dan. 12.3. <hi>They that bee wiſe, ſhall ſhire as the brightneſſe of the firmament: and they that turn many to righteouſneſſe, as the Starres for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> whom he had converted unto God, his <hi>Crown of rejoycing in the day of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.19. and St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us of an <hi>immar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſibilis gloriae corona, a Crown of glory that fadeth not away,</hi> which ſhall bee put upon every faithful Paſtors head at the laſt day by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and chief Shepheard of his flock the Church: as yee have it lively and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid forth, 1 Pet. 5.4. <hi>The Elders which are among you, I exhort, feed the flock of God which is among you, &amp;c. And when the cheif Shepheard ſhall appear, yee ſhall receive a Crown of glory that fadeth not away.</hi> Here is the faithful Paſtors <hi>Aureola,</hi> if they will needs have it ſo called.</p>
            <p>To which I will adde but one notable ſaying more of that famous Father St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Valcrius: Nihil difficilius, laborioſius, periculoſius Epiſcopi, aut Presbyteri, aut Diaconi officio: ſed apud Deum nihil beatius, ſi eo modo milit etur quo noſter imperator jubet: There is nothing more hard, nothing more laborious, nothing more dangerous than the miniſterial office: and yet with God there is nothing more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170143:44"/>(ſays hee) nothing more rewarded in heaven, <hi>if it bee faithfully executed as it ought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus yee have the third and laſt general head laid forth unto you, the great reward which ſhall certainly bee conferred upon every faithful Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And now Brethren, out of all theſe three main conſiderations which I have here mentioned unto you: that it is ſo high and weighty a Calling, that wee runne ſo great a hazzard in the negligent performance of it, and that on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſo great a reward remains for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that faithfully diſchargeth it: let both you that are this day newly initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into it by <hi>Ordination,</hi> and all of us alſo, whoſoever elſe are of the ſame mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial function, let us all bee ſtirred up to <hi>ſet our ſelves the more ſtrenuouſly about it, and with all carefulneſſe and watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for to manage it.</hi> That ſhall be my clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Labour to put in ure both the precept and the practice of the great Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul:</hi> his Precept unto <hi>Archippus,</hi> Col. 4.17. <hi>And ſay to</hi> Archippus, <hi>take heed to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery which thou haſt received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it;</hi> let that bee the utmoſt both of your and our indeavour, to fulfil the Miniſtery which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170143:45"/>And labour as well to follow the practical example of the ſame great Apoſtle, as a moſt renowned pattern and preſident for all Miniſters while the world ſhall ſtand, it is <hi>Act.</hi> 20.24. <hi>But none of theſe things move me, neither count I my life dear unto my ſelf, ſo that I might finiſh my courſe with Joy, and the miniſtery which I have received of the Lord Jeſus, to teſtify the Goſpel of the grace of God.</hi> Hee ſays, that no affliction whatſoever, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>bonds</hi> and <hi>impriſonment,</hi> nor <hi>martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> it ſelf, ſhould withhold him from fulfilling his Miniſtery, and ſo finiſhing his courſe with joy: agreeable to that Swannes ſong of his, which hee uttered when hee was ready to bee offered up in ſacrifice for the faith of the Goſpel, 2 Tim. 4.7. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed my courſe, I have kept the Faith: henceforth there is laid up for mee a crown of righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore this ſaying of his in the <hi>Acts,</hi> hee ſpake unto all the Elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> whom hee had ſent for unto him, propounding his own example before them, whereby they might learn how to fulfil their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: which is that which both ye, and all other Miniſters ought to bee alwayes lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how to perform.</p>
            <p>Which that ye may the better do, give me leave for a concluſion of all, to lay you
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170143:45"/>down briefly ſome helps and furtherances thereunto. I will firſt remove the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances, and then give you the helps.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Take heed of an ambitious and proud Spirit,</hi> of an high and domineering ſpirit, ſuch, as would not onely <hi>Lord it over Gods heritage,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, but alſo over your fellow brethren in the Miniſtery: for this is juſt <hi>Diotrephes</hi> his ſpirit, of whom St. <hi>John</hi> complains, that hee was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>One that loved to have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence,</hi> and to be leader of all, 3 Joh. 9. <hi>I Wrote unto the Church, but</hi> Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes <hi>who loved to have the preeminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, receiveth us not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed it was this that firſt brought in the <hi>typhus papalis</hi> in the Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They laboured for the primacy, and that by degrees uſhered in the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, for the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> had at firſt but <hi>primam ſedem,</hi> afore the reſt of the four Patriarchs of the Chriſtian Church; it was this ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and this ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which made him at length affect to be <hi>Epiſcopus Oecumenicus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though now Biſhops bee put down yet muſt every Miniſter among us beware of any riſings of a domineering ſpirit within him: for if as <hi>Luther</hi> was wont ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiouſly to ſpeak, that <hi>every man had a Pope in his belly:</hi> then ſurely much more did hee mean it of <hi>Clergy men,</hi> who have
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170143:46"/>been ever too much addicted to this fin.</p>
            <p>Beginne then to lay <hi>a low and deep foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in humility:</hi> eſpecially the better gifted any of you bee, or have the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts, as the more dangerous inlet unto pride: according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>knowledge puffeth up,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.1. And remember that qualification, which among the reſt, the ſame Apoſtle requires in thoſe which are to bee made Miniſters, 1 Tim. 3.6. <hi>Not a novice, leaſt being lifted up with pride, hee fall into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the Devil,</hi> he was very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful leaſt any Miniſter ſhould bee tainted with that <hi>Devilliſh</hi> and <hi>Luciferian</hi> ſinne of <hi>Pride,</hi> by which the Devils got ſo great a fall: <hi>How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, ſonne of the morning?</hi> Iſa. 14.12. which though it bee litterally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the great King of <hi>Babylons</hi> fall, yet myſtically of the Devils fall, in the judgement of Interpreters, who was once a good Angel, and a bright ſhining ſtar.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Take heed of a covetous ſpirit,</hi> of a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring deſire after preferments and gainful places: for nothing will ſooner Wyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw a Miniſter from a careful and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of his office, nothing will ſooner make him turn a <hi>Balaam, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170143:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. and nothing (if need bee) will ſooner make him turn from the truth, than that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that being <hi>given to filthy lucre,</hi> which both the great Apoſtles, do ſo much inveigh againſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. 1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 5.2. And that it often makes men <hi>ſwarve from the Truth,</hi> not onely experience in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Church hath made it manifeſt, but St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plainly ſo, 1 Tim. 6.10. <hi>The love of mony is the root of all evil, which while ſome have coveted after, they have erred from the faith</hi> (ſayes he) which is meant of <hi>fides quae creditur,</hi> and not of <hi>fides quâ creditur:</hi> of the faith which wee do beleeve, and not of that by which wee beleeve.</p>
            <p>Do none of you then turn <hi>ſecular Prieſts</hi> in the trueſt ſenſe: according to that of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.4. <hi>No man that warreth, intangleth himſelf with the affairs of this life;</hi> after hee had ſaid unto him in the verſe before: <hi>Endure thou hardneſs as a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And according to his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample towards the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in that memorable Apophthegme of his, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee every good Miniſters <hi>Motto, Non veſtra quaero, ſed vos, I ſeek not yours but you,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Take heed of a temporizing and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſpirit,</hi> as another vice which is a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170143:47"/>great obſtruction to the faithful diſcharge of a Miniſters office: when Miniſters are more ready by their practice, to interpret in the worſt ſenſe the doubtful reading of that place to the Romans, than in the beſt ſenſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. and are rather for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: rather for <hi>being fervent in ſpirit ſerving the time,</hi> than <hi>fervent in ſpirit ſerving the Lord.</hi> Although <hi>Beza</hi> ſayes, that in every authenticall ancient Greek Copy, it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo tranſlated in the vulgar <hi>Latine:</hi> and yet <hi>Eraſmus</hi> would needs render it, <hi>Tempori ſervientes,</hi> but there are few Schollers but know, how he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it too well by his practice, being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fiſh, nor fleſh, neither perfect Papiſt, nor perfect proteſtant, as it is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid of him now, and was ſo then, when hee lived in the beginning of <hi>Luthers</hi> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>But ſuch a baſe <hi>compliance with the times</hi> (bee they what they will) as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not a Miniſter of God, of all other men, ſo it will much cool his zeal to God and his truth; and by degrees take away all his fervour from an impartiall reproving of the ſins and corruptions of the time, which he ought to do.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Take heed of a vain glorious ſpirit,</hi> of all deſire of applauſe from men in the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, as the very bane of all
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170143:47"/>faithful Diſpenſing of the Goſpel: for this is for men directly to preach themſelves, inſtead of preaching Chriſt, which the Apoſtle doth ſo labour to ward off from himſelf, 2 Cor. 4.5. <hi>Wee preach not our ſelves, but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as hee explains it more fully, in his other Epiſtle to them, 1 Cor. 2.4. <hi>And my ſpeech, and my preaching, was not with entiſing words of mans wiſdome, but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the ſpirit, and of power.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is this powerful preaching, which muſt do the deed for the converſion of ſouls: not as if there were no uſe of an holy eloquence, which is an excellent gift of God, for then the holy ſpirit would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have noted it out unto us, that <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> was an eloquent man, Act. 18.24. and wee know that he had his part in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering that great Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had in planting of it: <hi>I have planted, Apollo watered, but God gave the increaſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.6. and there was St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> among the Antient Fathers, and St. <hi>Bernard</hi> among the middle age writers, who did excel in this gift, in their frequent preaching, and were the powerfulleſt preachers in their times.</p>
            <p>But when men will make uſe of this &amp; other of their gifts, onely for their own credit ſake, and to cry up themſelves in the Pulpit, without making the glory of God
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170143:48"/>and the good of others their cheifeſt and their only aim, this is that which will make a Miniſter of the Goſpel fall ſhort in his faithfulneſs, and to ſeek himſelf, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4, 6.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> that devout and learned Father, hath a very pious paſſage to this purpoſe, in an Epiſtle of his to <hi>Nepotian, Docente te in Eccleſia, non clamor populi, ſed gemitus ſuſcitetur: lacrymae auditorum, laudes tuae ſint; Let the many weeping eyes, the ſighs and groans of thy auditours, be thy commendation when thou preacheſt</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and not the vain applauſe of men,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is that which will commend thee with God, and with all good men.</p>
            <p>Thus having briefly removed the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances, let mee now more briefly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto you the helps and furtheran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and ſo an end.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Bee much in prayer,</hi> as that which will much help forward the fulfilling of your Miniſtry: for if Prayer be the Chriſtians daily exerciſe, then how much more ſhould it bee the <hi>Miniſters daily and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual exerciſe?</hi> And if any thing may bee obtained by Prayer, then how much need hath a Miniſter of God to bee fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent at it, who hath ſo many things to pray for, in behalf of ſo weighty a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? and if our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf ſpent a whole night in prayer unto God, when
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170143:48"/>hee was to chooſe his twelve Apoſtles, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them apart for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.12, 13. then how much farre greater reaſon, hath every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter among us, to bee much in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto him for himſelf, that he may bee able to go well thorough with ſo hard a task.</p>
            <p>The practice of great <hi>Luther</hi> is very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for this, and very exemplary for all of us Miniſters: who though he was a man of the moſt <hi>Heroical and undaunted ſpirit</hi> that we read of, yet he made a great deal of more uſe of <hi>his vehement ſpirit of Prayer,</hi> whereby to ſet upon the work: for ſo wee find it recorded of him, that he did <hi>Tres ad minimum horas, easque ſtudiis aptiſſimas in orationem ponere;</hi> ſpend no leſſe than three hours daily by himſelf in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and thoſe which were the fitteſt hours for his ſtudy too; And I beleeve that he loſt no time in ſo doing, towards his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial employments.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Bee diligent in ſtudy and meditation,</hi> that yee may this way alſo bee the better furniſhed and prepared for ſo weighty a function: for as all our ſtudying will do little good, except wee further it by our frequent praying, ſo all ur praying will not bee ſufficient except wee join in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious <hi>ſtudy</hi> and <hi>meditation</hi> with it, both which together are the means appointed by God.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170143:49"/>
            <p> And therefore is is an injunction given by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy: Till I come, give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrin,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. as well to read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as to preaching: and ſo much more to reading, becauſe ſo much the better to preaching; and in the next verſe but one, <hi>Meditate upon theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them, that thy profiting may appear to all.</hi> Whence <hi>Luther</hi> again added this ſecond help to the former, in another ſententious ſaying, which hee was wont to utter: <hi>Tria faciunt Theologium, Oratio, Meditatio, Tentatio:</hi> theſe three things make an accompliſht Divine, Prayer, Meditation, and Temptation; for as for the latter of the three, himſelf was ſo much exerciſed with the Devils Temptations, that hee thought him the moſt experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Divine that was moſt troubled with them: and indeed next unto Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, I have not read of one more aſſaulted with them, than this greateſt <hi>Engine</hi> of the Churches reformation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Labour to Preach out of love to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſouls,</hi> Which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath redeemed at ſo high a price: as St. <hi>Paul</hi> intimates to the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> when he charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to <hi>feed the Church of God, which hee hath purchaſed with his own bloud,</hi> Act. 20.28.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing, <hi>what ſhall it profit a man if
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170143:49"/>hee gain the whole world, and loſe his own Soul,</hi> as our Saviour ſayes? how ſhould wee Miniſters bee moved with bowels of Compaſſion unto the ſouls of men, to draw as many of them as poſſible wee can out of the Devils kingdome, it being our office to <hi>ſave Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which end, mee thinks there is ſuch a remarkable ſaying of the great Apoſtle concerning himſelf, that I know not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all his Epiſtles which hath more wrought upon mee as a Miniſter, or may more move any Conſcientious Miniſter, if ſeriouſly thought upon: it is, 2 Cor. 12.15. <hi>I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you, though the more abundantly I love you, the leſſe I bee loved.</hi> Here was love indeed to the ſouls of his people.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And Laſtly, <hi>Labour to preach out of love to the Lord Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>great Shepheard of the ſheep;</hi> and whoſe they are, <hi>John</hi> 10.14. which if wee do, it will make us the better do the former duty; for our love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> will force us to bear love to mens ſouls, which hee hath ſo dearly bought. And if once the love of Chriſt come to conſtrain us, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, then wee ſhall play the zealous and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters to purpoſe: it is only this that can make us become martyrs if need bee, and <hi>to lay down our lives for the Sheep,</hi> and for the <hi>cheif Shepheard too:</hi> ask old <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170143:50"/>elſe, that moſt Antient Father, when a little before his glorious martyrdome he uttered theſe moſt affectionate words, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor meus crucifixus eſt; my Love was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore was it, that no leſſe than three ſeveral times together, <hi>Christ</hi> ſaid unto St. <hi>Peter: Simon ſon of Jonas; loveſt thou mee? feed my Sheep,</hi> John 21.17. which I could wiſh both you, and I, might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hear ſounding in our ears, as a moſt ſoveraign motive to fulfil our miniſtry to the utmoſt of our indeavours: <hi>Loveſt thou mee? feed my Sheep.</hi> And which as it was in a manner the concluſion of our Saviours words, a little before his Aſcenſion into heaven: ſo it ſhall be the concluſion of my Exhortation unto you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170143:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
